<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>XXI divines (whose names are here-under affixed) cleared of the unjust criminations of Will. Penn in his pretended just rebuke for their epistle to a book, entitled, Quakerism no Christianity ..., / by John Faldo.</title>
            <author>Faldo, John, 1633-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40788</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12364559</idno>
  <idno type="VID">60366</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248616622</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12364559</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 914:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>XXI divines (whose names are here-under affixed) cleared of the unjust criminations of Will. Penn in his pretended just rebuke for their epistle to a book, entitled, Quakerism no Christianity ..., / by John Faldo.</title>
                  <author>Faldo, John, 1633-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Dorman Newman, and Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 104.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Penn, William, 1644-1718.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Faldo, John, 1633-1690. --  Quakerism no Christianity.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60366:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60366:1"/>
            <p>XXI. DIVINES (Whose Names are here-under affixed) CLEARED, Of the Unjust Criminations of <hi>Will. Penn;</hi> IN HIS Pretended <hi>JƲST REBƲKE</hi> for their Epistle to a Book, entituled, <hi>QƲAKERISM NO CHRISTIANITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>William Penn</hi> proved neither Christian, nor a man of Common Modesty, or Honesty.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Divines vindicated,</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Tho. Manton,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Tho. Jacomb,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> John Singleton,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Cole,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Doelittle,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Samuel Smith,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Ben. Needler,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Richard Baxter,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Gouge,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> John Yates,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> John Sheffield,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Anth. Palmer,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Richard Mayo,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Andr. Parsons,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Will. Jenkyn,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Geo. Griffith,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Matth. Barker,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Watson,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Will. Co<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Stephen Ford,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Will. Ca<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN FALDO.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Tim. 3. 9</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For their folly shall be made manifest unto all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Similia loquentes (haeretici) fidelibus, non solum dissimilia sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt, sed &amp; <hi>Contraria;</hi> &amp; per omnia plena blasphemiis, per quae interficiunt eos, qui per similitudinem verborum diss<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mile assertionis corum in se trahunt <hi>venenum. Ir<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n adv. haer.</hi> l. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binson,</hi> at the Kings-Arms in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> and at the Golden-Lyon in S. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:60366:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60366:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>One and twenty Divines clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of the unjust Crimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of</hi> William Penn.</head>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I were addicted to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie,</hi> and took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure therein for its <hi>own</hi> sake, it were an Affection enough <hi>Culpable:</hi> And to chuse the Quakers Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Concerns for the Objects of my Inspection, and Opposition, to <hi>that</hi> end, would sufficiently detect me of <hi>Imprudence.</hi> But duty to God, and love to Truth and Souls, hath engaged me in that Work, which (howsoever unpleasant <hi>in it self,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the notice of men, who cannot relish any thing relating to those they esteem (and that justly) a <hi>Brain-sick</hi> People) would be a <hi>just</hi> reflection upon the Generation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>we</hi> live, if none should industricusly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, and <hi>thorowly</hi> manage it; so many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60366:3"/> thousands being infected with that <hi>Mortal Delirium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I <hi>first</hi> entred upon the Detection, and Confutation of the Quakers Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, I was not so ignorant of their <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper,</hi> as to promise my self an Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from the <hi>highest</hi> affronts, that their vilifying and reproachful Reflections could put upon me. But as my design was not <hi>only</hi> just, but also <hi>necessary;</hi> so my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in its management, hath been so <hi>clear</hi> from doing that People <hi>any</hi> injustice, that all the Bryers and Thorns of <hi>their</hi> Invectives have not made the least scratch in my <hi>inward</hi> Tranquillity. The Lord is my witness, how <hi>careful</hi> I was to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent their Principles and <hi>Manners</hi> with all <hi>Candor,</hi> and to produce proofs proper, faithful, and convincing. How many <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> hours were spent to that end, let the Work it self inform thee.</p>
               <p>I have once vindicated my Book, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Quakerism no Christianity,</hi> from <hi>William Penn</hi>'s <hi>pretended</hi> Answer; not because his Answer <hi>merited</hi> a Reply, but rather to confirm my first Charge, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the weakness, and <hi>shuffling</hi> (to say no worse) of my Adversaries Defence and Criminations. I have offer'd my Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60366:3"/> and the most <hi>horrible</hi> Principles I have charged the Quakers with, to a <hi>personal</hi> debate with <hi>William Penn,</hi> the greatest Undertaker for the Quakers. But this, though tendred with the most <hi>prudent</hi> Circumstances, for avoiding Inconveniences, and rendring the Contest <hi>effectually</hi> sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying; he hath as industriously avoided, as if the <hi>day</hi> were a <hi>terrour</hi> to him: And hath rather chosen with <hi>Shimei,</hi> to keep his <hi>distance,</hi> and so go on Cursing, Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and castong stones.</p>
               <p>Many <hi>Worthy</hi> Persons, whose Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is above the <hi>reach</hi> of <hi>Wil, Penn</hi>'s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, having written an Epistle, as well <hi>Monitory</hi> to all professing Christianity, as Recommending my Book; <hi>William Penn</hi> hath given them a <hi>taste</hi> of his <hi>gall,</hi> and loaded them (so far as <hi>his</hi> credit will pass) with crimes to be <hi>abhorred;</hi> besides his <hi>usual</hi> Exclamations to beget an opinion of their <hi>undoubted</hi> guilt, with such as can hear and understand a <hi>noise,</hi> better than <hi>Demonstration.</hi> And in very deed, the greatest advantage of <hi>Penn,</hi> and other Quakers, lies in their <hi>high</hi> Professions, <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement</hi> Protestations, and <hi>seemingly</hi> most serious Appeals; there remaining that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> Charity in most of Mankind, as will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60366:4"/>
                  <hi>hardly</hi> permit them to believe, that any man should be <hi>so vile,</hi> as to <hi>cover</hi> Fraud and Wickedness under <hi>such Pretences.</hi> But as the <hi>most</hi> guilty Malefactors (having learned that Maxim, That <hi>Impudence is the Perfection of Vice)</hi> do most <hi>abound</hi> with Protestations of their <hi>Innocency,</hi> and Exclamations on their Accusers; so <hi>wary</hi> persons will not have their judgments thereby <hi>determined,</hi> omitting that <hi>Test</hi> which will better enable them to give a <hi>just Sentence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>like</hi> Wisdom and Justice I intreat of <hi>all</hi> men, who are concerned to judg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us in <hi>this</hi> Controversie; which I should hardly have repeated, but for the Vindication of <hi>so many Divines,</hi> whose Reputation <hi>Penn</hi> hath endeavoured to wound through <hi>my sides,</hi> and whose Works praise them in the Gates. I desire those who have <hi>my</hi> Books by them, to <hi>compare</hi> Mr. <hi>P's</hi> Accusation and them <hi>together,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>his</hi> directions in his <hi>margin,</hi> and let their <hi>own eyes</hi> be their <hi>Judges.</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, is an easie way to <hi>confute;</hi> and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath changed his <hi>nature,</hi> if he rage not most, where his cloven foot is most <hi>discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> My labour herein is my duty; my reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for well-doing, will be my crown. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60366:4"/> now Reader, I leave thee a <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and address my self to <hi>William Penn,</hi> the man of my present Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>IN your Preface to your <hi>Work,</hi> as all your <hi>good</hi> Notions (in themselves) are abused to set off a <hi>bad</hi> Cause, and put Deformity on those you intend to bait; so <hi>some</hi> parts of it (though fronted with <hi>Confidence)</hi> have that <hi>apparent</hi> untruth and miscarriage, as calls for <hi>Detection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You say, <hi>The invincible Faith, and Patience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 3.</note>
                  <hi>and Hope of those holy Ancients, that so heartily espoused it</hi> (the Quakers Cause) <hi>stand before you as so many bright Examples and Encouragement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I presume you mean by these <hi>holy Ancients, Enoch, Noah, Abraham,</hi> the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, Primitive Christians, and the Martyrs for Christianity, and its <hi>Purity</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days; or at least you would have us <hi>understand</hi> you so. But is it not strange that all these should be Quakers, and but your <hi>Precedents,</hi> and not one of all the Enquirers into <hi>Antiquity</hi> should be aware of it, till <hi>you</hi> had found it out? But how came you by this Invention, especially you Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> if you practice your own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? For you say; <hi>But I will assure them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>W. Penn's</hi> Spirit of Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 23.</note>
                  <hi>they shall yet grope in the dark, till they come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the daily obedience of the Light; and there rest contented to know</hi> only <hi>as they</hi> experience; <hi>and not from a ravening comprehending brain, that would in its unregenerated state, grasp at the</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60366:5"/> clear Mysteries, (or <hi>Clean Mysteries,</hi> as you told me it should have been) <hi>of the Kingdom, into which fleshly Comprehensions and Notions can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter: But all must be as unlearned from their First-birth, Education, and Traditional read-Knowledg, as he is unmanned, that is again be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a little child, before the secrets of God's Work come to be made known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is this the voice of <hi>William Penn?</hi> If what you say be <hi>true,</hi> as you would have <hi>us</hi> to think; I doubt you are as <hi>counterfeit</hi> a Quaker, as you are a <hi>Christian.</hi> Have you been <hi>unlearned</hi> from Education, and Traditional <hi>read-</hi>Knowledg? I think not; unless, as your <hi>Bedlam</hi> Quaker Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seller told me, you write all against me by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration</hi> (if you would be better informed where he dwells, than in my <hi>last,</hi> I now tell you, he dwells right against the Burial-place wall) but then 'tis what you can give us no <hi>evidence</hi> of. But I must needs conclude, That seeing you know <hi>only by experience,</hi> you cannot know that those holy Ancients were <hi>Quakers,</hi> or bright <hi>Examples</hi> of what is <hi>your</hi> Religion, they being dead before you were <hi>born.</hi> But if you know them to be such any <hi>other</hi> way, we have your own word for it, that you <hi>grope in the dark:</hi> And so let it pass.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> these, and such-like things of you and your party, make you the wonder of <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi> And if they have so much <hi>Charity</hi> for you, as to believe you say as you <hi>mean,</hi> or <hi>mean</hi> as you <hi>say,</hi> (which must be a great deal) yet at <hi>least,</hi> they judg of you to be an <hi>infatuated</hi> People. And if <hi>W. P.</hi> be such an one, what are the <hi>puny</hi> Quakers?</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60366:5"/>
               <p> I must not let pass your next words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Arrest for <hi>Defamation;</hi> (I mean your words, not your <hi>body,</hi> for I must be so careful, having to do with the <hi>Captious,</hi> and such an one as will create <hi>ex musca Elephantem:) So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb. &amp;c.</hi> p. 3.</note>
                  <hi>have the many and great attempts of men of divers, yea opposite Interests, to render us unfit for the Earth.</hi> Where have they <hi>told</hi> you, that this was their <hi>design?</hi> Where did they say, they would have the World perswaded, that 'tis not fit the Quakers should be suffered to <hi>live?</hi> Sure I am, you must read <hi>me backward,</hi> if you intend to fix this Charge upon <hi>me;</hi> for I have told you, <hi>That it is far from my Principle, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fald. <hi>Ep: to Quak. no Chri. in fine.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>natural temper also, to intend your Persecution; and that I know nothing that men who are your Adversaries can do more, to promote your Tenets and Party.</hi> Tell me, if you can, where I have retracted, or contradicted <hi>those</hi> words. It seems 'tis a Crime to interpret your <hi>words,</hi> who speak <hi>Barbarisms</hi> enough; but 'tis your right to interpret our <hi>hearts</hi> as you <hi>list.</hi> But thus you are an <hi>Ʋsurper</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Throne, who is the <hi>only</hi> Searcher of hearts: And that which is worse, you pretend his Authority for it. I shall prove what I say, from no less Author than your <hi>instar Papae, George Fox;</hi> who saith, <hi>And you that have not that which is infallible to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Great mystery of the great Whore,</hi> p. 5.</note>
                  <hi>judg in you, know not the Spirit of Christ; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you judg of persons or things, that have not the infallible judgment, nor have the spiritual man; neither have you the Word of God in your hearts, nor Christ which is Eternal and Infallible: All which the Quakers have to judg persons and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60366:6"/> things.</hi> No wonder if the Quakers believe <hi>all</hi> you say, how <hi>apparently soever untrue.</hi> I do not judg a Turk, a Heathen, or a Jew not fit to be suffered to live upon Earth; though I judg them not fit to be <hi>esteemed</hi> Christians, and know them to be <hi>Enemies</hi> to Christianity as well as <hi>you;</hi> but yet something more <hi>fairly,</hi> as they are <hi>openly</hi> such, and you <hi>Treacherously.</hi> But I proceed to your <hi>Self-</hi>magnifying news, which never reached our eyes or ears, till <hi>your</hi> Pamphlet reported it; <hi>viz. We have been long</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb.</hi> p. 4.</note>
                  <hi>threatned with a report of the joynt-endeavours of many Ministers—But we no sooner received and look'd into the Book, than we saw our selves under a very great Disappointment. For, instead of some new Essay, behold an old Discourse new-vamp'd; or a new Impression of a Book twice largely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, and as some think, effectually answered: I mean,</hi> John Faldo<hi>'s Quakerism no Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is more than <hi>possible,</hi> that this Report is but the Figment of your own brain. And if you <hi>dream,</hi> that the overthrow of your cause is <hi>so</hi> difficult a task, that it requires the <hi>joynt-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours</hi> of <hi>such</hi> in a <hi>new</hi> Essay; you may gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your self with your <hi>ungrounded</hi> fancy, and thank your <hi>selves</hi> for your disappointment. I think I have the <hi>means</hi> to know their minds and motions concerning <hi>your</hi> affairs better than <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of you, or <hi>all</hi> of you: And I assure you, I have never heard that it entred into their <hi>thoughts;</hi> but on the contrary, they are so well satisfied that your cause is <hi>determined,</hi> by what hath been done <hi>already,</hi> that they have thought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60366:6"/> fit to give their Attestation in the Epistle you have attempted to bespatter.</p>
               <p>Yet 'tis <hi>strange</hi> (but <hi>like</hi> your self) that you should pretend an expectation of a <hi>new Essay,</hi> a <hi>new</hi> Book, containing the <hi>joynt endeavours of many Ministers;</hi> and then tell us you look'd for it: But <hi>where?</hi> in <hi>my old one</hi> new-printed and vampt (as you phrase it:) But why should such <hi>Gnosticks</hi> as <hi>you</hi> look for a <hi>new</hi> Book in an <hi>old</hi> one; and one that carried in its <hi>forehead</hi> the <hi>old</hi> Inscription of <hi>Quakerism no Christianity,</hi> and by the single <hi>old</hi> Author <hi>John Faldo?</hi> Who can suppose you not guilty of <hi>wilful</hi> mistakes, and free from the affronts of <hi>such</hi> disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who go to work thus blind-fold-like? and lay your words so <hi>well together,</hi> that your <hi>next</hi> line calls you—for that which went <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> before it;</p>
               <q>Oportet—esse memorem.</q>
               <p>Having past your Preface, which deserves such a <hi>Censure;</hi> I now meet with your <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BƲKE OF ONE AND TWENTY DIVINES,</hi> and must in the future passages of your Pamphlet, have still in my eye, that nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seous <hi>impar &amp; Congressus, W. Penn,</hi> One and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Divines; <hi>W. Penn against</hi> One and twenty Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; and that at no more fair, and modest a Weapon than a <hi>REBƲKE.</hi> A <hi>Rebuke</hi> from <hi>W. Penn</hi> a Quaker, a Youngling, a Boy, <hi>comparatively,</hi> to One and twenty <hi>men,</hi> to One and twenty <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Gospel, Elders by <hi>Office;</hi> such, whose <hi>Office</hi> set aside, are many
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60366:7"/> of them, for Learning and Parts, men of <hi>Name;</hi> scarcely any of them but of years enough to be your <hi>Father,</hi> and near one half of them old enough to be your <hi>Grand-father.</hi> And not an <hi>implicite,</hi> or a Rebuke in <hi>general</hi> terms, but a down-right Rebuke to them by <hi>name,</hi> a Rebuke to their <hi>teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am sure if the <hi>Scripture</hi> had been your Rule (if not their Office, yet) their <hi>Age,</hi> and the hoary-heads of <hi>some</hi> of them, would have commanded a more <hi>respective</hi> behaviour, though putting off the Hat be accounted by you an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious and uncivil Ceremony. Methinks it had become you rather, to have <hi>fronted</hi> your Reply with a <hi>modest Enquiry</hi> into their Epistle; or a <hi>sober Expostulation.</hi> But nothing could <hi>suit</hi> your unbridled Passion, and <hi>scornful</hi> Spirit, but a <hi>REBƲKE.</hi> If the Light of Nature forbid a <hi>Saucy</hi> Deportment to our <hi>Elders,</hi> by far, this carriage is no Commendation of your <hi>Morality,</hi> which you presume we will allow you, while denying you to be a <hi>Christian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Porch and Title being so <hi>Faulty,</hi> I suspect a <hi>foul</hi> house <hi>within.</hi> And your first Entertainment consists of <hi>Quibbles,</hi> and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Censures and Insinuations: <hi>But let us hear</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s. Rebu.</hi> p. 5.</note> (say you) <hi>what use, you the great Men of Ʋses make of this Introduction.</hi> I say no more to you for this, but wish for your <hi>own</hi> sake, and <hi>theirs</hi> whom you influence, that you were rather a great Man of <hi>Ʋses,</hi> than a man so guilty of many, and the greatest <hi>Abuses;</hi> as will not be only said, but proved.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60366:7"/>
               <p> In the same Page you are at your <hi>sport</hi> again: <hi>Render the Quakers better than they are! There is little fear you will. You may turn Pelagian in the case, and exclude all Divine assistance: For I hope none are so ignorant in this Age, as to think Men of your Stamp need special Grace to keep you from the sin of rendring the poor Quakers better than they are.</hi> Verily Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> if those Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Persons you <hi>scoff</hi> at were turned Pelagians, it would advance them by <hi>many</hi> steps nearer to Quakers. For herein the Pelagians and you are <hi>agreed:</hi> They held, That the powers of <hi>Nature</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Voss. in hist. Pela.</hi> lib. 3.</note> were <hi>sufficient</hi> to preserve them from <hi>all</hi> sin, yet cried up <hi>Grace</hi> to keep them from publick <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred;</hi> while they meant no more by Grace, than God's bestowing on all men such a <hi>Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nature:</hi> And you cry up <hi>Inspirations, and Divine Assistance;</hi> and yet mean no more by it, than the Light and Power <hi>within,</hi> which <hi>every</hi> man hath; and is indeed no more but the <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Faculties by you improved at a <hi>lower rate</hi> than the <hi>Heathens.</hi> This Principle of yours, you express <hi>out-right,</hi> in your ungodly <hi>Mockery</hi> at <hi>special</hi> Grace in these words; <hi>It is the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians special Grace that saveth; for Moralities</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s. Rebu.</hi> p. 31.</note>
                  <hi>part, alas! she is a poor Heathen, an Alien, an Infidel, without the Pale of the Church, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Covenant; but then it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of the Scotch one.</hi> Whether you learn'd this <hi>Christian Drollery</hi> of your <hi>Admired Ben. Johnson,</hi> or our more Modern <hi>Railers,</hi> I know not: But the Scab is <hi>catching,</hi> especially by those <hi>nigh</hi> of Kin. I perceive corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and <hi>prophane</hi> Wit are your <hi>Darlings;</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60366:8"/> your Nature is as greedy to suck in the Poyson of the one, as of the other.</p>
               <p>Your Censure of their Prologue (and their design in it) to the Epistle, little commends your Modesty or <hi>Charity:</hi> scil. <hi>Or else to give a greater</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 5.</note>
                  <hi>credit to your Work, than your selves perhaps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it deserves.</hi> What is this but to <hi>insinuate,</hi> That they deserve to be suspected for a pack of gross and impious <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> who <hi>designedly</hi> abuse the holy and reverend Name of God; and pretend to a <hi>sense</hi> of it, but to cover their <hi>wilful</hi> lying? If this take with your Readers, and they believe their <hi>good</hi> words, <hi>excellent</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be (as you phrase it a little after) <hi>but a trick to decoy people,</hi> your work is done. But I doubt not ere I have done with you, to set this Brand on him who more deserves it, and discharge you with the Character of <hi>Homo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teratus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I come to those things of yours, which <hi>look</hi> like Arguments; but not being animated with <hi>truth,</hi> they will be of small <hi>strength.</hi> The first is no less than a pair of <hi>Dilemma's;</hi> but all your <hi>storms</hi> cannot wreck the Objects of your Fury upon the <hi>Scylla</hi> or <hi>Charibdis</hi> of those <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> straits: <hi>Either</hi> (say you) <hi>you have read, or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 5.</note>
                  <hi>not read the Book ye recommend.</hi> Very right; and what of either? <hi>If you have not, certainly you have done ill to recommend it.</hi> Thus far you are pretty fair: But what if they have read it? Why then you say, <hi>They manifestly entitle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to all the evil of it.</hi> But now Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> I must stop your <hi>Career:</hi> For, if the Book an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the <hi>Recommendation,</hi> and have not in it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60366:8"/> any thing that may be <hi>otherwise</hi> mischievous to the Reader, though there should be some <hi>lesser</hi> evils in it, they do not entitle themselves to <hi>them.</hi> And the most they say of the Book is, <q>That in it the Quakers and their Principles <note place="margin">Min. Ep. to Quak. no Christ. in fine.</note> are more thorowly investigated, than in any Book which <hi>they</hi> have seen—And that for Matter, Proof, and Stile, they judg it to be especially useful for those who need or desire Information about the Quakers and their Principles.</q> Now I will confess to you (if it will do you any service) that I have shewed much <hi>infirmity</hi> in the Management of it, to which I should be loth to <hi>entitle</hi> those Worthy Persons, you would <hi>deform</hi> with any Scars you can find <hi>there;</hi> and <hi>who,</hi> if they had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken that Work, might have managed it much <hi>better</hi> than I, and to the greater <hi>exposing your evil Cause.</hi> But for all the faults you have <hi>really</hi> found in it, they may give you <hi>your</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without reaping to themselves any <hi>cause</hi> of shame or repentance; which will be proved, as the matter comes to hand.</p>
               <p>Now I shall consider your <hi>second Dilemma;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reb.</hi> p. 6.</note> which amounts to thus much, <hi>That if they have not compared the Citations, which are the strength of the Book, with the Books themselves, their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation is by rote. If they have, you will prove, That they have offered great violence to their Ʋnderstandings, in giving their Approbations.</hi> Great words! which will shortly vanish into <hi>smoak and vapour.</hi> For the <hi>first</hi> of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences (if I should grant that which I neither know, [nor you have proved) it is lame: For if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60366:9"/> they have not made that <hi>Compare,</hi> they may have read some, or many of your <hi>numerous</hi> Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, containing the <hi>same</hi> things. And they might have been present at the numerous Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>August</hi> 28. 1674. (I am sure some of them were.) They might have heard <hi>there,</hi> or from <hi>sure Testimonies,</hi> that I there offered my Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to a <hi>personal</hi> Test, and a <hi>publick,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Quakers would <hi>call</hi> for it: Whereas you have hitherto accounted it your <hi>prudence,</hi> not to take me at my <hi>word.</hi> They may also have read your Answer, or Rejoynder, wherein you acknowledg all you are pleased to <hi>recite,</hi> except three or four. They may have read my Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wherein I <hi>provoked</hi> you to meet me with <hi>impartial</hi> Judges, and I would undertake to prove my Faithfulness, against the <hi>worst</hi> of your Calumnies: To which you are silent. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the truth of the Citations depends on matter of <hi>Fact;</hi> wherein to deal untruly, <hi>so oft</hi> as must be to <hi>enervate</hi> any of my <hi>Charges,</hi> must be so <hi>wilful</hi> a Treachery, as no man ought to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect a Professor of Godliness guilty of, till he have merited it by some apparent miscarriage to discredit him. And I protest <hi>seriously,</hi> that if I did not certainly know, that <hi>ungodly Crime</hi> were your <hi>frequent</hi> Guilt, I should hardly be perswaded to <hi>disbelieve</hi> many falshoods in point of <hi>Fact,</hi> which your Books are cram'd with: But all this is said <hi>ex gratia.</hi> They have pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough to conduct their own affairs in this matter, and need not you or I to tell them what Evidence is a ground for them to go on; and you having <hi>proved</hi> nothing,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60366:9"/> I might have let this pass without further notice.</p>
               <p>Your <hi>second</hi> Consequence you refer the proof <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> of till <hi>anon;</hi> and I shall attend till then for it. In the next place you charge me, That <hi>the most</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>of the Principles I charge upon you to be yours, are not so laid down by any one of you;</hi> nor say you, <hi>Sayable by any of you upon your real Principles.</hi> But should you not have proved this? You in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance only in <hi>one Charge;</hi> which you say, I will defend but by <hi>Consequence;</hi> scil. <hi>That there is no other Judgment, Heaven or Hell, than what is within us in this life.</hi> And you add, <hi>That it is so far from being your Principle in your words, that it is as inconsistent with the</hi> truth <hi>of your Creed, as darkness is with light.</hi> But what a <hi>set</hi> are you at for an <hi>instance,</hi> out of the <hi>most</hi> of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples I charge you with, that you give <hi>one</hi> (and but one) which I no-where find charged upon you in <hi>those</hi> words, which you pretend to be <hi>mine.</hi> I have examined my <hi>Catalogue</hi> of your Errours, and there they are not; I have taken some pains in searching the Book for them, and there I find them not. And though you give us but a <hi>single</hi> instance, and in a <hi>different</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you tell me not where I may find it by quotation of Chapter, or Page. Is not this striking your <hi>own</hi> sword into your own <hi>bosom?</hi> Yet let me tell you, that though the <hi>matter</hi> of those words of yours (not mine) being in your Creed, render your Creed <hi>untrue</hi> with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: I shall not baulk at proving it to be <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily</hi> your Creed, much more <hi>consistent</hi> with it.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60366:10"/>
               <p> If I prove, That neither the <hi>Bodies,</hi> nor the <hi>Souls</hi> of men shall be subjects <hi>capable</hi> of any reward after <hi>this</hi> life by <hi>your</hi> Principles; then I <hi>prove,</hi> That it is not only <hi>consistent</hi> with <hi>your</hi> Principles, but <hi>apparently</hi> necessary by <hi>your</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>That men shall have no other Judgment, Heaven or Hell, but what they shall have in this life.</hi> And in the <hi>first</hi> place I shall prove, That you deny the <hi>Resurrection of the Body;</hi> and so, that <hi>that</hi> part of man shall be no more capable of a Heaven or Hell after its <hi>death,</hi> than that which is, and ever shall remain without <hi>life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> in the presence of about an <hi>hundred</hi> persons, acknowledged, That <hi>he did not believe, that his Body should rise again after its death.</hi> This is <hi>plain</hi> English, and from a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of no less <hi>esteem,</hi> but far longer <hi>standing</hi> among the Quakers than your <hi>self.</hi> These <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part</hi> 2. p. 136. <hi>Answ. to</hi> Faldo, <hi>p.</hi> 200.</note> words of his I cited in my <hi>Quakerism no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity,</hi> and you <hi>repeat</hi> them in your Answer, without denying them to be <hi>his</hi> words; which you would have done no doubt, if he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them to <hi>you.</hi> But on the other hand you say, <hi>But what if he did say</hi> so, <hi>and I should second him? would it follow that we deny a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection?</hi> I acknowledg, that you profess the belief of an <hi>Allegorical Resurrection:</hi> But this is but a <hi>shuffle,</hi> and a <hi>silly</hi> evasion; the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> being of the Resurrection of the <hi>Body,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Unbelief being of the Resurrection of <hi>his Body.</hi> Before I proceed any farther, I shall open the Readers eyes to the <hi>A Resurrection</hi> (which you say is not <hi>denied</hi> by <hi>Whiteheads</hi> words) from the Learned <hi>Fisher</hi> the Quaker,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60366:10"/> who went to <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>somewhat. Ye have</hi> (saith he) Moses <hi>and the Prophets</hi> within; <hi>viz. This written, spoken, manifested in you,</hi> Quod tibi ne vis fieri, alteri ne seceris. <hi>And</hi> (retro) <hi>Whatever</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fisher. Velata quaedam revel.</hi> p. 4.</note>
                  <hi>ye would that men should do unto you, so do ye even to them. This</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>is the Law, or</hi> Moses, <hi>and the Prophets. But if ye will not be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished nor perswaded by</hi> Moses <hi>and the Prophets, neither will ye be perswaded by such of us, who were once</hi> dead in sin <hi>with you, but are now</hi> risen <hi>to life, by the Power of God, which is his</hi> Light, <hi>and in the same sent to speak unto you from the DEAD.</hi> Here your Resurrection is set out to the <hi>life,</hi> wither some other fine knacks of the Quakers, that serve for a <hi>shelter</hi> in a time of <hi>need.</hi> But I shall plow no farther into your <hi>infidelity</hi> in <hi>this</hi> point, but with your <hi>own</hi> Heifer.</p>
               <p>Having thus far <hi>revolted</hi> from Christianity to Heathenism, or <hi>Atheism;</hi> you lay hand on <hi>their</hi> Weapons, where-with to fight against the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>revealed</hi> Truth of God, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion you are <hi>apostatized</hi> from: <hi>Either</hi> (say you) <hi>the Resurrection of the Body must be without that (gross elementary) matter, or it must not: If it must, then it is not that same</hi> numerical <hi>Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penn's <hi>Answ. to</hi> Fal. <hi>p.</hi> 201.</note>
                  <hi>and so their</hi> proper <hi>and strict taking of the word</hi> Resurrection <hi>they must</hi> let go: <hi>If it must not be without that same gross matter it dyed with, then I affirm it cannot be</hi> incorruptible; <hi>because it will carry with it that which will render it</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible <hi>ad infinitum.</hi> It is not now my business to examine the Philosophy or Logick of your Argument; but to discover your <hi>Opinion.</hi> And take you which way we <hi>will,</hi> you here deny the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60366:11"/> Resurrection of the Body. But you say fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that you may not be thought of <hi>our</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, after all this: <hi>I say, we cannot see, how that which is of dust should be eternal, whilst that from whence it came is by nature but temporal.</hi> And I believe you, so long as you leave the Light without, and above you, and are guided only by the Light <hi>within</hi> you, which is <hi>natural,</hi> and receiveth not <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se</hi> things of God.</p>
               <p>Being thus plunged in the Dungeon of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, you have the wit to tell me that, which a Boy understanding his Accidence, would be ashamed of; <hi>viz. And that which is yet most of all irreconcileable with Scripture, and right Reason, is, That the less and change of Nature from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible to incorruptible, natural to spiritual, should not make it another Body. In vain do such</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 202.</note>
                  <hi>dispute against the Popish Transubstantiation as an absurd and impossible thing, who themselves are guilty in a case of the like nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder the less at your other absurdities, and your confidence wherewith you counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance them, seeing you talk so <hi>ignorantly</hi> of the Popish <hi>Transubstantiation.</hi> They say, That the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bell de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uch.</hi> l 3. c 18. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ch. ad P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch. ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>n. frui.</hi> p. 830.</note>
                  <hi>substance</hi> of the Bread is changed into the real <hi>Body</hi> of Christ, and into his <hi>Divinity;</hi> and that it <hi>ceaseth</hi> to be <hi>Bread,</hi> while the <hi>accidents</hi> of Bread <hi>remain:</hi> And we say, That in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>substance</hi> of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is raised, or quickned again; but its quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and <hi>accidents</hi> are altered, or <hi>changed.</hi> I know not any of us are <hi>so</hi> ignorant, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. That by being made spiritual <hi>(i. e.</hi> rarified and made more <hi>subtile)</hi> that, it is changed into a <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60366:11"/>
               <p> Let it be observed also, That the Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body which I affirmed they <hi>deny,</hi> and which Opinion <hi>you oppose,</hi> I gave an account of in <hi>these</hi> words: <q>The raising again to <hi>life</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quak. no Christ.</hi> part. 2. p. 122. last impres. <hi>p.</hi> 238.</note> and from the dust and <hi>corruption,</hi> the bodies of men and women, <hi>however</hi> disposed of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their natural death or <hi>dissolution.</hi>
                  </q> This you have <hi>denied;</hi> and shew me if you can in any <hi>Quakers</hi> Writings, that they believe the <hi>body,</hi> after dissolution, or any <hi>part</hi> of it, shall be <hi>quickned,</hi> and raised to life in <hi>any</hi> manner or form whatsoever. Thus I have made good my first task, That you deny the Resurrection of the Body. I shall now prove, That you deny their Souls, after the <hi>death</hi> of their Bodies, to be subjects <hi>capable</hi> of reward.</p>
               <p>My first Argument I shall draw, from what you affirm the Spirits and Souls of men to be. And first, I shall give you the testimonies of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fisher. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam revel.</hi> p. 17.</note> an <hi>early</hi> Quaker, and a man able to tell his tale as <hi>punctually</hi> as any of you: <hi>And whereas ye Query,</hi> (saith he) <hi>Whether the said Spirit of manis mortal, or immortal? I answer, It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and neither mortal nor corruptible; but that immortal and incorruptible Seed of God, even something of that living Word which is said to be made flesh.</hi> And this he saith is essentially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutive of <hi>Adam</hi> in his pure state, and of every Regenerate man.</p>
               <p>But yet plainer and more general: <hi>And is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fox <hi>great M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>st.</hi> &amp;c. p. 16.</note>
                  <hi>not</hi> (saith <hi>Fox,</hi> your great Oracle) <hi>that of God, which comes out from God? is not that of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing—and so Divine?</hi> (speaking of the Soul.) Again (saith the same Author) <hi>Is not the Soul
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60366:12"/> without beginning come from God?—It is not horrid Blasphemy to say, The Soul is a part of God, for it came out of him; and that which came out of him, is of him.</hi> Magnus Bine <hi>saith, The</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id in eod.</hi> p. 29.</note>
                  <hi>Soul is not infinite in it self: And</hi> Richard Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>saith, It is a spiritual Substance. Now consider</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. in eod.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>what a condition, these called Ministers, are in: They say that which is a spiritual Substance, is not infinite it its self, but a Creature.</hi> The same Oracle saith moreover, <hi>Is not the Soul without beginning, coming from God, returning INTO God again?—</hi>Hath <hi>this beginning or ending? And is not this Infinite in its self?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I will put it to the verdict of any rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal man, Whether you in affirming the Spirits or <hi>Souls</hi> of men to be something of that <hi>living</hi> Word, which is said to be <hi>made flesh;</hi> to be of the <hi>Being</hi> of God, and so <hi>Divine,</hi> without <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> a <hi>part</hi> of God, <hi>Infinite</hi> in it <hi>self,</hi> not a <hi>Creature,</hi> do not render it a subject uncapable of any rewards; especially, considering, that 'tis said by you to be returning <hi>INTO</hi> God again. I shall not take notice here of your Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemies in talking of a <hi>part</hi> of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many of these passages, among others, I cited in my Book; and some of them you took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of in your Answer; and but <hi>some, which</hi> you thought you could best <hi>warp</hi> to a tolerable sense; though when you had done all, a <hi>half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted</hi> man might pronounce you guilty from your own evidence.</p>
               <p>I pray review <hi>the</hi> strong Contradiction of <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ. to Quak. no Christ.</hi> p. 192.</note> your own, to what I charged you with: <hi>We do for ever</hi> (say you) <hi>renounce any such Principle,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60366:12"/> as that the Soul of man, simply as such, is the very Essence and Being of God.</hi> Do you deny here, the Soul of man to be the <hi>very Essence and Being of God?</hi> No; your <hi>Simply as such,</hi> is <hi>too sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> a shuffle to blind a Reader, not blind <hi>before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I having given you the matter of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I now give it in <hi>form</hi> thus; <hi>If (according to the Quakers Principles) the bodies of men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death shall never be quickned, and raised to life again, much less to a life that shall never end; and the Souls of men are of God's own Being, a part of him, and shall return into him again: Then (according to the Quakers Principles) there is no part of men, which after death, shall remain sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects capable of a Reward, a Heaven, or Hell: But the former hath been proved; threefore the latter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I had from <hi>undeniable</hi> grounds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by <hi>Consequence,</hi> That the Quakers deny or <hi>disown</hi> a blessedness or misery in <hi>another World;</hi> yet finding them confidently asserting, That they owned <hi>eternal</hi> Rewards: For the curing of my <hi>mistake</hi> (if I were under such a thing) I made this <hi>fair</hi> Proposition to them; <q>Let them profess that they believe a happiness <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quak. no Christian.</hi> part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 141. impr. <hi>ult.</hi> p. 248.</note> to be enjoyed by men or women, after their bodies are rotted to dust, distinct from the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of God, or that which they had not a <hi>thousand</hi> years before they were <hi>born (i. e.)</hi> to be <hi>IN</hi> God, from whom (as of his <hi>Being) they say</hi> the Soul came; and it will be news to me, and all that are <hi>acquainted</hi> with <hi>them.</hi>
                  </q> And was not this enough to engage you to profess your Faith in this matter, if you had any beyond
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60366:13"/> what I apprehended? But all your <hi>Evasions</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this Proposal <hi>prevented,</hi> and the true state of your Faith about eternal Rewards, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, in your <hi>Answer</hi> you take no notice of my Proposal. In my <hi>VINDICATION</hi> I charged you with the neglect of it; and after I had repeated the former matter, I added, <q>This <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vindic. of Quak. no Chr.</hi> p. 90.</note> I proposed for the <hi>evading</hi> of all their <hi>delusive</hi> terms, and that I might draw out of them an acknowledgment of the genuine truth, if they had any such in the Treasury of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. But as I charged <hi>Penn</hi> before, so I do now again (and with him all thorow-Quakers) that his silence to this matter, concludes them guilty of not owning a future Reward in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other World, or a Life to come.</q> One would have thought all this more than enough, to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke</hi> you to speak <hi>out,</hi> if you had any thing to say to the purpose. But you Rejoyn in a Book of 437 pages, and are as dumb to this Proposal as ever, though as streperous as ever in Rants and Reflections. This being a matter of such <hi>moment,</hi> that it <hi>alone</hi> determines the <hi>Controversie,</hi> I took the occasion you gave me, to be thus <hi>full</hi> in its discussion. And now let sober men, yea, let the Lord <hi>judg</hi> between you and me, who of us are guilty of <hi>injury</hi> in <hi>this</hi> matter.</p>
               <p>I shall now farther defend the <hi>justice</hi> of my laying down <hi>your</hi> Principles not <hi>always</hi> in <hi>your own</hi> words, although the <hi>like dealing</hi> with others would be <hi>really</hi> unjust.</p>
               <p>Most Professors of Religion, and all that are not ashamed, or <hi>afraid</hi> to have their Principles generally understood, are plain and <hi>open</hi> in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60366:13"/> their <hi>expressions</hi> of them, and industriously de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to be understood, and use such <hi>terms</hi> as <hi>others</hi> use, and <hi>understand</hi> by them what they <hi>mean:</hi> But you walk in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and like Gypsies, have a Canting of your <hi>own,</hi> in which you speak to <hi>one anothers</hi> understandings; while strangers to your Opinions and ways, may as well understand <hi>Welsh,</hi> or <hi>Hebrew</hi> (though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bred or learned therein) as they can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand <hi>you.</hi> I know you have boasted of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Gifts and Tongues too; but this plotted way of clouding your meaning, is all the Tongues that ever I could find you attained by Quakerism; and by which, your Conferences with persons unacquainted with you, hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred you deservedly <hi>Barbarians</hi> to them, while you esteem them Barbarians in <hi>spiritual</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, for not understanding your <hi>uncouth</hi> phrases.</p>
               <p>Some-newcoyn'd phrases you use, which are your proper and peculiar Mintage (except you had them from <hi>Jacob Behem) ex. gr.</hi> Miracles in <hi>Spirit,</hi> The <hi>Seed</hi> in captivity, A <hi>measure</hi> of God From the Spirit inwardly <hi>ravening, Ravening Comprehending Brain, fleshly comprehensions, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penn's <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> p. 23. <hi>Page</hi> 14.</note>
                  <hi>read-Knowledg,</hi> Vulturous eye; with many more. The four last are your <hi>own,</hi> and <hi>three</hi> of them are jumbled together within the compass of <hi>five</hi> lines. To these I may add a multitude of words and phrases you use in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with others, but your meanings by them, are not the <hi>same</hi> with the <hi>generally-</hi>received <hi>import</hi> of the words. For instance, By persons in Covenant with God, you mean such persons as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60366:14"/> are <hi>without sin;</hi> yea, that have <hi>no sin</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their <hi>natures,</hi> and no other.</p>
               <p>This is verified by a great man among you (with <hi>most</hi> of your <hi>Leaders</hi> in their Writings:) <hi>Now</hi> (saith he) <hi>where sin is remaining in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Crisp's <hi>Alarm,</hi> p. 16.</note>
                  <hi>there the Covenant with Hell and Death is not broken, neither are such in Covenant with God.</hi> A hard, cruel, and untrue saying. By the being under the <hi>Devils</hi> power, you mean the same thing, as appears by the words next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the fore-cited: <hi>But are yet under the power of the Prince of the air, what-ever they profess.</hi> So by being <hi>in sin,</hi> you mean such as have any <hi>remains</hi> of sin in their nature: <hi>And the death of Christ is of no value unto them, because they are yet in sin.</hi> These words are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the former, and applied to the same persons. I shall give you one <hi>loud</hi> proof more of this falshood, and <hi>fallacy. Be it known unto you, in the Name of the God of Heaven, that where sin remains, there the Devil is Prince and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. in eod.</hi> p. 13.</note>
                  <hi>Ruler.</hi> Who understand these terms <hi>so,</hi> but your selves?</p>
               <p>Let me give you a Demonstration, that such <hi>abused</hi> terms force me to give your Principles not <hi>alway</hi> in your <hi>own</hi> words. I find one of your chief Ministers writes thus, <hi>For this end is Christ manifested, to destroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and to redeem OƲT OF the fall. And this</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Parnel <hi>Shield of the Truth,</hi> p. 48.</note>
                  <hi>we witness, who through the Lamb our Saviour, do reign above the World, Death, Hell, and the Devil; but none can witness this, whose eye is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, looking at a Redeemer afar off, and still live in sin.</hi> Now, Reader, suppose I were to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60366:14"/> give their Principle from these words, it will bear according to their <hi>true</hi> meaning, that they hold, That <hi>none can be redeemed from the Devil, from the fall, who look to a Redeemer afar off, which is no otherwise to be understood, but of the the Person of Christ ascended.</hi> But there being added these words, <hi>and yet live in sin:</hi> If we take it in our sense it clear them; for we hold, all that live in sin, to have no <hi>Gospel</hi> sincerity, no <hi>true</hi> faith; and so though they expect Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the true Christ who is ascended, are not delivered and redeemed <hi>from the Devil and Law.</hi> But take <hi>living still in sin,</hi> in the sense of the Quakers, for <hi>a not-</hi>being freed from all remains of sin in our <hi>natures,</hi> and the cover is taken off, and the blind removed.</p>
               <p>And that I may shew you how full of such strange meanings a short Sentence of theirs may be, take notice, that by <hi>We witness,</hi> they mean not a testimony to <hi>others;</hi> but their own <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,</hi> or having it by <hi>Inspiration:</hi> None of them will deny this. But there is a <hi>worse Snake</hi> in the grass: For by the <hi>Lamb their Saviour,</hi> they mean not the same numerical man, Jesus the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> who was crucified at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> for he is the Redeemer we <hi>look at afer off;</hi> but they mean, the Light <hi>within</hi> them. And because 'tis very <hi>strange,</hi> as well as very <hi>corrupt,</hi> I shall give a proof of it: <hi>Here was the Light shone out of darkness</hi> in <hi>John</hi> (John 1. 9.)—Then God sent him to <hi>bear witness unto</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Morning Watch,</hi> p. 5.</note>
                  <hi>the Light which</hi> in him (these two last words are put in a different Letter in my Author) <hi>was made manifest, that all in the Light might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60366:15"/> and he called to others to behold him, and said, he was the LAMB OF GOD,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Who that gives their Principles always in their own words, can possibly render many of their Tenets (especially those they most indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striously hide from such whom they would not have to understand them) intelligible to others? What I have said are their own words, are such; and what I charge them with beside, I give in <hi>their</hi> sense, though not in their <hi>words;</hi> which is as necessary, as it is to render that in <hi>English</hi> to a <hi>mere</hi> English Reader (that he may understand it) which is spoken or written in <hi>another</hi> Tongue. And I have so far consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Contexture</hi> of their sayings, as that I am very well armed to <hi>prove</hi> each particular to be <hi>their</hi> sense in the <hi>same</hi> place, whenever I am <hi>called</hi> thereunto.</p>
               <p>By Election and Reprobation, they mean God's chusing of <hi>Christ,</hi> and rejecting the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and sin;</hi> which is proved by the following Citation. Quest. <hi>And doth Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mith<hi>'s Catech.</hi> p. 9.</note>
                  <hi>stand in the Natures, or Seeds of Light and Darkness?</hi> Answ. <hi>Yes it doth so; for the Seed of Light is Christ, whom God hath elected and chosen before the Foundation of the World; and the Seed of Darkness is the Devil, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which is reprobated for ever.</hi> Is it not clear here as <hi>Sun-beams,</hi> what kind of things are the subjects of eternal Rewards or Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by their Principles? I should be too <hi>tedious,</hi> if I should <hi>here</hi> enumerate their <hi>ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meant</hi> phrases, and give the proofs at <hi>large;</hi> as, that by <hi>Carnal Ʋnderstanding and Imaginations,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60366:15"/> they mean the use of <hi>Humane</hi> Reason; by the <hi>Will of the Flesh,</hi> our choice and derermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, however <hi>rational,</hi> or according with the <hi>Scripture,</hi> if not by the Motion and Inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Light <hi>within;</hi> by <hi>Christ,</hi> the Light <hi>within;</hi> by being <hi>out of the Power of God,</hi> not adhering to the <hi>motions</hi> and impulses of what they call Christ, or the Light <hi>within;</hi> by the <hi>Man Christ, the spiritual Man,</hi> the Light within <hi>still;</hi> by <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> a Christ crucified <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;</hi> by the <hi>Righteousness of Christ</hi> justifying them, the works done in <hi>their</hi> bodies by the strength (they say) they receive by the Light and Power within; by <hi>Christ's flesh and blood in their flesh,</hi> a body of spiritual flesh, blood and bones, which (they say) came down from Heaven, and <hi>tabernacled</hi> in the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> while he was upon earth, and <hi>now</hi> dwells in the Quakers.</p>
               <p>If they would please to give us a <hi>Dictionary</hi> of their Words, Phrases, and Interpretations, all their Murther would <hi>out:</hi> But in the mean time their Adversaries (I mean to their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) must study them out of their Writings, and converse as they do, who give us the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations in English of Foreign Languages; and this I have done faithfully (so far as I have expressed) in my <hi>Key to the Quakers phrases.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> I shall follow you at the <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Reb.</hi> p. 7.</note> heels, with less pains, and more advantage. You quarrel with the Reverend Divines (never the less <hi>Reverend</hi> for all the dirt you can fix upon them) for not consulting your <hi>Answers</hi> to my Book. I assure you, if <hi>you</hi> wish they all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60366:16"/> had read and weighed them throughly, you and I are agreed in <hi>somewhat:</hi> For I know not any more <hi>sure</hi> way to my <hi>Vindication,</hi> and your <hi>Condemnation,</hi> than a <hi>due</hi> comparing our Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. But yet you <hi>only</hi> tell them what they <hi>should</hi> have done to render them blameless (at least with <hi>you)</hi> but you prove nothing with your <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> though you make bold Conclusions. But what should we expect <hi>more</hi> from a man, whose <hi>mettal</hi> is no where but in his words and <hi>flourishes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They had been prudent <hi>indeed</hi> by the rule of <hi>Contraries,</hi> if they had followed <hi>your</hi> advice, and upon your <hi>strong</hi> Reasons; <hi>viz. But if you must needs be so liberal, methinks your Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation had better been bestowed upon his VIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATION, since his writing that, proveth this wanted it; and if it wanted then, its wants</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 7.</note>
                  <hi>it still, and yet it seems the Book vindicated, must be the Defence of the Vindication, and all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn I am like to have to my Rejoynder, bating the Epistle,</hi> &amp;c. Can you be <hi>sober,</hi> and believe that men of <hi>Reason</hi> will account this your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning <hi>sober?</hi> Must a Vindication be taken for a <hi>Condemnation</hi> of what it <hi>vindicates,</hi> without more ado? Are you not <hi>a cast and a condemned</hi> man, and the Quakers <hi>Cause</hi> with you, by your <hi>own</hi> Logick? For your writing in their Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, proves they <hi>want</hi> it. And doth not your attempts to vindicate your <hi>Answer,</hi> shew by this Figure of yours, that it was a defective or faulty thing? But farther, must not a Book be <hi>reprinted,</hi> but for its own Vindication? By your Logick, the <hi>oftner</hi> Books are <hi>reprinted,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60366:16"/> the <hi>worse,</hi> and more faulty they are <hi>proved</hi> to be. This came into your <hi>head,</hi> and then it must be <hi>let drop</hi> on your <hi>Book</hi> for a piece of <hi>wit</hi> that the World had need of, to fright them from <hi>reprinting good Books,</hi> especially against the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi> Why do you complain of my not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering your Rejoynder? Is this the way to provoke me to it, seeing such a thing must be for a Vindication of my first Book, and you tell me such a course proves it wants it? Well then, seeing I do not believe my Book wants a Vindication, or your Rejoynder deserves an Answer, I may take my rest with more pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence than you scrible; especially considering, that <hi>your credit</hi> will be Vindication <hi>enough</hi> of any thing against <hi>your reproaches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You might with more <hi>prudence</hi> have told such a Block-head as I, <hi>you generally fling Infallibility</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 7.</note>
                  <hi>at us—as if it were a Capital sin to be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured,</hi> than so many <hi>Learned</hi> men: For your making Infallibility and Assurance to be the <hi>same</hi> thing, is a <hi>broad</hi> Symptom of your <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> The next passage you transcribe (with your Reply to it) hath undone your <hi>Cause.</hi>
                  <q>The Quakers preach another <hi>Gospel,</hi> and endeavour to <hi>seduce</hi> well-meaning Souls, to whom they speak in <hi>unintelligible</hi> words; and from whom they hide the <hi>poyson</hi> of their <hi>Antifundamental</hi> Doctrines.</q> What say you to this? Why, <hi>Here is a great deal in a little:</hi> And so say I too. But you say, 'tis <hi>very sowrely said:</hi> And I say, 'tis very truly and <hi>soberly</hi> said. But shall we take you at your next words, <hi>Were it as true, as it is false, the day were yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60366:17"/>
               <p> If it were no more <hi>true</hi> than <hi>you</hi> would have it <hi>accounted false,</hi> it were false and <hi>black enough.</hi> But I shall not be beholding to your <hi>grant;</hi> we are rich enough in <hi>Truth and Evidence,</hi> to live without your Alms; and strong enough to turn the Quakers out of their Usurpations, against their wills.</p>
               <p>You may say, <hi>They make not the least offer to prove it.</hi> But you anticipate their Answer, of <hi>John Faldo's having done it for them,</hi> and make your Exceptions against <hi>him;</hi> as first, an <hi>Irreverent abuser of God.</hi> God forbid! But what God? Alas 'tis of the Quakers Gods or <hi>Idols,</hi> the <hi>Light within them,</hi> their <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Spirits,</hi> which they call by that name. Pardon me Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> if when you set up a <hi>stock,</hi> and call it a God, I do not presently fall down and <hi>worship</hi> it. But you say again, <hi>I am an abuser of the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And who will expect <hi>you</hi> should say <hi>otherwise</hi> of any, who write against yours? But I suppose the greatest abuse you <hi>stomach</hi> is, my not reverencing the Quaker<hi>-Dutch woman's</hi> declaring in <hi>Dutch,</hi> to a Meeting of <hi>English Quakers,</hi> who <hi>confessed</hi> they understood not a <hi>word</hi> she spake, yet were confident she spake <hi>by the Spirit,</hi> for they all found <hi>refreshings.</hi> I pray pardon me this wrong, though I never repent it to my dying day.</p>
               <p>But in the third place you say, <hi>And which is more to my contentment, whatever it be to his and yours; some, and no Quakers too, think I have prov'd him such.</hi> More to your Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! why was it at all to your Contentment, that I should abuse God, and the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60366:17"/> But it seems, that some thinking you had proved me <hi>such,</hi> who were not Quakers, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding grateful and <hi>contenting</hi> to you. Verily a <hi>small</hi> Approbation of your attempts, contents you greatly; for I doubt not but there are other silly people in the World besides the Quakers, who may at <hi>least,</hi> be so good-natur'd, and be so credulous as to <hi>think</hi> so. But would you not think it very strong and pertinent for me to tell you, that <hi>some,</hi> and neither Presbyterians nor Independants did tell me; that you did not write to confute me, but <hi>merely</hi> to shew your wit; so remote were you either from the <hi>matter,</hi> or the <hi>truth;</hi> and so much in love with <hi>Witticisms,</hi> that no hedge of <hi>exact</hi> Expressions would hold you, but you would break out the stake of one <hi>Substantial</hi> word or another for a passage. Yea, should I tell you, that some such said, that your Friends were so confident of all you said to be true, and well, that if you put out my Book in <hi>your name,</hi> they would take it to be a very good Book, and all in it very true: And I assure you, 'tis no less than some have said, and would not be <hi>perswaded</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p>Give me leave in the next place to answer your Question, and I shall not need to be beholding to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rebuke, &amp;c.</hi> p. 8.</note> any to take <hi>my</hi> word that I answer you truly: <hi>And let me ask you</hi> (say you) <hi>if it be another Gospel to own Remission of sin, and Eternal Salvation by the Son of God; and both as he appeared above</hi> 1600 <hi>years ago in the flesh, and as he reveals himself with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in Power and Spirit?</hi> If your Opinions in <hi>these</hi> matters, were the same with what is received by the generality of understanding and <hi>serious</hi> Christians, you would have expressed them in some or other of <hi>their</hi> Forms of Confession; but you love the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60366:18"/> Clouds and <hi>By-paths,</hi> that your sense may not be discerned. And in truth, you not only <hi>may,</hi> but <hi>do hold</hi> another Gospel, than what <hi>we affirm</hi> is the Gospel of Christ, for all the truth that is <hi>expressed</hi> or <hi>meant</hi> by you in <hi>this</hi> form of words. It is a sad thing that your Principles and Manners are <hi>so</hi> bad, that they that know them, will take all your words with <hi>suspicion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What your <hi>Eternal Salvation</hi> is, I have proved already. That by the <hi>Son of God,</hi> you understand the Divinity <hi>only,</hi> or Godhead, is so common in <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ox<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reat my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ery,</hi> p. 71.</note> your Prints, that none who are acquainted with them, are ignorant of it; yet for the Reader's sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, I shall cite some of your Authors. And first, <hi>George Fox</hi> thus: <hi>And Christ's Nature is not Humane, which is earthly, for that is the first</hi> Adam's. Next to him, take <hi>Pennington</hi>'s verdict in these words: <hi>This we certainly know, and can never call the bodily Garment Christ; but that which appeared and dwelt in the body.</hi> Here, that which <hi>dwelt</hi> in the <hi>body,</hi> which was the Godhead, and that <hi>only,</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be Christ. And in the former, Christ's <hi>Humane Nature</hi> is <hi>denied</hi> in so many <hi>words:</hi> Yea, you hold those to be <hi>false</hi> Ministers, that preach a <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mith<hi>'s Primmer,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. 9.</note> Christ <hi>without</hi> us; and those only <hi>true</hi> Ministers, who preach a Christ <hi>within.</hi> All this your great Author <hi>W. Smith</hi> saith in so many words, <hi>They that are</hi> false <hi>[Ministers] preach Christ</hi> without, <hi>and bid people believe in him as he is in</hi> Heaven above; <hi>but they that are true Ministers, they preach Christ</hi> within, <hi>and direct people to wait to feel him in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and so to believe in him, as he makes himself manifest</hi> in <hi>them.</hi> The Child is made to reply (for you are to take notice, 'tis a Primmer or Catechism:) <hi>This is a great difference in their</hi> Doctrine, <hi>for one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60366:18"/> to preach Christ</hi> without, <hi>and another preacheth him</hi> within. The Father answers, <hi>Yes, it doth make a</hi> great <hi>difference, and hath no more</hi> fellowship <hi>than the East and the West.</hi> What think you of your <hi>Gospel now?</hi> or what do you judg those <hi>against</hi> whom you write will censure it to be, wherein such a <hi>Salvation,</hi> and such a <hi>Saviour</hi> is preached? and to preach Christ <hi>without,</hi> and Christ <hi>within too,</hi> hath no <hi>more Fellowship than the East and the West?</hi> What can you say, to put a <hi>colour</hi> on this, consistent with owning Jesus the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> who rose, and is ascended above the visible Heavens, to be Christ? You know I gave you this Citation in my <hi>first</hi> Book; but you thought good (with most of the <hi>greatest</hi> weight) to let it pass without <hi>any</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. Let the Reader <hi>judg,</hi> if this be not <hi>excellent</hi> Doctrine to teach to <hi>young Children.</hi> While you tell us we must hearken to the <hi>Light within,</hi> to teach us what is <hi>necessary</hi> to believe and practise, and that is <hi>sufficient,</hi> you have <hi>Primmer</hi> and <hi>Catechism without,</hi> to teach your Children to deny the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of the Gospel.</p>
               <p>I shall now examine the other part of your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel; <hi>scil. And both</hi> as <hi>he appeared above</hi> 1600 <hi>years ago in the flesh, and as he reveals himself WITHIN in Power and Spirit.</hi> Your great <hi>fallacy</hi> lies in the word <hi>AS,</hi> which is a word of <hi>Likeness,</hi> or <hi>Comparison.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to evidence as clear as <hi>light,</hi> that you hold that the Son of God appeareth now. <hi>AS</hi> he did then; and that you, or some others of you are, according to <hi>your Opinions,</hi> as <hi>truly,</hi> I say as <hi>truly,</hi> Christ, as Jesus the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> I shall give suffificient proof.</p>
               <p>In my first Book I wrote <hi>these</hi> words, <q>They do <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Quaker. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Christian</hi> part 2. <hi>p</hi> 70. impr.</note> not <hi>deny</hi> that there <hi>was</hi> such a man as Jesus the <hi>Son of Mary;</hi> and that God was in him, or rather
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60366:19"/>
                     <hi>Christ</hi> was <hi>in</hi> him:</q> But this is <hi>no more</hi> than they profess of <hi>themselves,</hi> that Christ, as God, and the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> is <hi>in</hi> them. Would not any one judg, that you should <hi>deny</hi> this Charge with as great violence and <hi>exclamation,</hi> as any in the Book? and that many impertinent, frothy, and clamorous passages in your <hi>Answer,</hi> ought to have given place and room, for your <hi>clearing</hi> your selves of <hi>this</hi> charge, if it were not your <hi>due?</hi> You cannot say, you did not <hi>observe</hi> it; for in your Answer you <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat</hi> my words <hi>thus, He says they do not deny, that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Answ. Quak. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Christ.</hi> 155.</note>
                  <hi>there was such a man as Jesus the Son of</hi> Mary; <hi>and that God, or rather Christ, was in him: But this is no more than they profess of themselves, that Christ, as God, is in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I read this <hi>Repetition</hi> of my Charge, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be overwhelmed with a <hi>floud</hi> of Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; but <hi>contrary-wise,</hi> I am not so <hi>stroaked</hi> by you for any <hi>passage</hi> in my Book: <hi>He hath done us</hi> (say you) right <hi>in two respects, which may a little answer for the ill language he giveth us in our Charge: First, That he acknowledgeth we own that there was</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ib.</note>
                  <hi>such a man as Jesus the Son of</hi> Mary <hi>(in contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to abundance of our Adversaries) and that God was in him, which makes up our Christ.</hi> Here you are so far from denying this Charge, that you own it to do you <hi>right.</hi> And let it be observed, that God dwelling in <hi>Jesus,</hi> doth not make up (as you call it) your Christ <hi>numerically,</hi> as <hi>excluding</hi> any other than Jesus the Son of <hi>Mary;</hi> but <hi>specifically,</hi> which answers to my <hi>saying</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Opinion, which <hi>say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> you commend. This were <hi>enough,</hi> but I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Burrough</hi>'s testimony.</p>
               <p>A Christian soberly, and <hi>seriously</hi> proposing this Question to him, <hi>Whether the Word was made flesh
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60366:19"/> more or oftner than once?</hi> He replies to him in this <hi>rude</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Burrou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Works Folio, <hi>p</hi> 29, 30.</note>
                  <hi>manner; In this Query thou art manifest what thou art, and where thou art, and what spirit thou art of, a Reprobate, a Child of Darkness.—this Query comes from thy polluted mind. The Light condemns thee, and all thy Generation eternally. The Word made flesh we witness, which dwells amongst us, and we behold his glory, whereby we witness thee, and all thy Generation to be in the Sorcery and Witchcraft.—But thou Dragon, that would devour the man-Child; thou the Dragon, with thy Angels, art cast into the Earth. For thy other nineteen Queries, thou hast con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured them up in the Black-Art, out of the bottomless pit.</hi> I shall not animadvert on every part of this Text, so <hi>pregnant</hi> with the Quakers <hi>mischievous</hi> Principles, and monstrous Manners. But was not this <hi>furious</hi> railing Reply, instead of <hi>answering</hi> the Question <hi>negatively,</hi> a strong <hi>evidence</hi> that you hold that the Word was made flesh <hi>more than once,</hi> as <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> as he was at any <hi>one</hi> time? Moreover, if the phrase, <hi>We witness,</hi> be rendred into the English <hi>you</hi> mean by it, one Clause of his Answer should be thus read; <hi>The Word made flesh we</hi> experience, <hi>which</hi> dwells <hi>among us, and we</hi> behold <hi>his glory.</hi> This evidence amounts to no less than yours before cited.</p>
               <p>I shall add one evidence <hi>more,</hi> out of your <hi>own</hi> Writings, which scarce needs an <hi>Interpreter: And</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W. Penn'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oynder to</hi> Faldo, p. 311.</note>
                  <hi>those who at this day do</hi> feed <hi>upon the</hi> history <hi>of the</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily <hi>appearance</hi> (yet honorable in its place <hi>and know not a breaking through the Vail, by witnessing a measure of the</hi> same <hi>Divine Wisdom, Power, Righteousness, Grace, and Truth, revealed and born forth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; they are but carnal, fleshly Christians, being unacquainted with the formation of the Christ of God IN THEMSELVES; which is the opening
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60366:20"/> of the mystery of Christ, GOD MANIFEST IN THE FLESH.</hi> The <hi>same Divine Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> relates to these words a few lines foregoing, <hi>Of which he is the fulness, whose transcending glory was vailed by that body of flesh he wore; i. e.</hi> the <hi>Divine</hi> Nature which dwelt in the <hi>Body</hi> of Jesus. What can be a more full proof that <hi>God manifest in the flesh</hi> (or <hi>appearing</hi> in the flesh, which is the same sense) spoken peculiarly of Jesus Christ, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. (and of him as his peculiar) is by you in your <hi>own</hi> words, made common to <hi>all,</hi> who are not (as you call them) Carnal, and <hi>Fleshly</hi> Christians. And you leave out the word <hi>WAS</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> to hide your <hi>Blasphemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I remember, that in some of your Answers to me (though I cannot readily find the place) you say, That <hi>you do not say that the</hi> fulness <hi>of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head dwells in you.</hi> To which I answer first, that your phrase of a <hi>Measure of God,</hi> respecting his <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,</hi> is your (peculiar) Blasphemy; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God is <hi>essentially,</hi> there is <hi>whole</hi> God, the <hi>infinite</hi> God. But farther, I will prove, that you hold the Light <hi>in you</hi> to be as <hi>infinitely</hi> God, as can be <hi>expressed. Will. Smith</hi> tells his Child in his Prim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, of the Light <hi>within the Child,</hi> the Light <hi>in its Conscience,</hi> that <hi>All power in Heaven and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>immer,</hi> 14.</note>
                  <hi>Earth is in it.</hi> So that here is the fulness of the Godhead dwelling in <hi>your bodies</hi> (by <hi>your</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples). But that I may give you full measure, pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed down, and running over, I will give you one Citation more: <hi>We believe</hi> (saith <hi>Smith) that Christ</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>techis.</hi> 64.</note> in <hi>us</hi> doth <hi>offer up himself a living Sacrifice to God for us, by which the</hi> wrath <hi>of God is</hi> appeased <hi>to us—and</hi> this is he <hi>in whom our Faith standeth, the</hi> one Mediator <hi>between God and man, the</hi> man <hi>Christ Jesus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60366:20"/>
               <p> Now let all impartial men judg of your <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical</hi> Equivocations, to hide your <hi>Anti-Gospel,</hi> and Antifundamental Doctrines. With what a forehead did you write <hi>such</hi> a Rebuke to <hi>such</hi> men, for writing so <hi>very</hi> a truth? I esteem this your <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable</hi> folly to be, what God hath permitted as a <hi>farther</hi> occasion to <hi>open</hi> your <hi>hidden</hi> things of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; for which I bless him, and I hope many others may do the like, for these Snares being more manifestly discovered: <hi>The wickèd is snared in the work of his own hands,</hi> Higgaion Selah, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9. 16.</p>
               <p>The next work that comes to my hand is, to consider what you say hath a very bad <hi>Consequence.</hi> But I will transcribe your <hi>own</hi> words; <hi>viz. For the other part of your Accusation, That we should</hi> say <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb.</hi> p. 8.</note> one thing, and mean another, <hi>it is by Consequence to call us the worst of Knaves: By how much a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in matters of Eternal moment, is more impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than any cozenage about things of this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have <hi>said</hi> it, I shall now <hi>prove</hi> it, and <hi>you</hi> have given us the <hi>Consequence.</hi> I doubt not but the Reader is so well satisfied <hi>already</hi> of the truth of this, That you say <hi>one</hi> thing, and <hi>mean</hi> another, that he will think <hi>farther</hi> proof needless. But I will add a little <hi>ex abundanti:</hi> The Quaker saith, <hi>That</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to</hi> Faldo<hi>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Quaker. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Christ.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Light is in the Scriptures, prove that; or tell me what one Scripture hath Light in it.</hi> Here is the greatest <hi>denial</hi> that may be of the Scriptures, or any <hi>one</hi> Scripture having <hi>Light</hi> in it. But <hi>W. Penn</hi> gives the <hi>meaning</hi> to be, <hi>There is not spiritual, living, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Light in the Scriptures; but a descriptive, and declarative Light they carry with them of the true Light.</hi> Now would any man take the Quakers phrase to mean as <hi>you say?</hi> What need had he to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60366:21"/> tell them there was not liying and essential Light in them, every body knows that; and his <hi>saying</hi> was a universal Negative in the <hi>highest</hi> terms.</p>
               <p>Quaker: <hi>So amongst the words, you find how the Saints in some things walked, and what they practised;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>orning-<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>atch,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>45.</note>
                  <hi>and then you strive to make that thing to your selves, and to observe it, and do it as near as you can: and here you are found Transgressors of the just Law of God, who saith;</hi> Thou shalt not make to thy self any graven Image, nor the likeness of any thing: <hi>Now what difference is there in the ground betwixt you and the Pope, though in the appearance there seem to be so great space.</hi> This, one would think, were very <hi>plain</hi> English. But you tell us, that he means <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>s Answ. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Quak. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Chri.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 98</note> quite other things: For say you, <hi>Take</hi> Will. Smith <hi>in his own sense and belief, and all is well.—He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that all those real Experiments of other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (of which the Scriptures are full) talk'd unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally over by ungenerated spirits, can be no ways beneficial. Nay, that what Idea's and Notions they may have to themselves of the holy Ancients enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, while altogether unacquainted with them; are but a kind of Images, which their believing in, and bowing to as indispensible Gospel-truths, is to be reputed nothing below Idolatry it self.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Either he or you, must <hi>notably dissemble</hi> here. How doth what you say is <hi>Smith</hi>'s sense, <hi>appear</hi> in his <hi>words? W. Smith</hi> speaks <hi>expresly</hi> of the Saints <hi>practices, and how they walked;</hi> and you give his meaning to be of their <hi>experiments and enjoyments. Smith</hi> calls their <hi>doing</hi> like them as near as they can <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and you give his meaning to be of unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate persons <hi>talking</hi> them over. If <hi>this</hi> were <hi>his sense,</hi> which is so far off from the true import of the words in the <hi>English</hi> Tongue, and we must
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60366:21"/> have <hi>such Interpretations</hi> to understand the Quakers meanings, it is past all doubt, that you say <hi>one</hi> thing, and mean <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you say farther, <hi>And if you measure us by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> p. 9.</note>
                  <hi>our words, you must grant that either you understand us not, or we mean very good things; for you say else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, that our obnoxious Tenets are usually maskt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der expressions doubtful, unintelligible, or under Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Orthodox phrases.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Either you are very ignorant of your <hi>own</hi> sayings, or your understanding <hi>doubly</hi> dark and <hi>vitious.</hi> When you say, The <hi>Soul is not a Creature, is a part of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in it self;</hi> That <hi>all power in Heaven and Earth is in the Light within;</hi> That <hi>they are false Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters that preach Christ without us:</hi> Must we needs say you mean <hi>very good things,</hi> if we measure you by <hi>your words?</hi> yea certainly, if saying you <hi>abound with Blasphemies,</hi> be to say you mean very <hi>good things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in your Report, you <hi>let drop a material word,</hi> for you repeat it, <hi>That our obnoxious Tenets we usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mask,</hi> &amp;c. whereas they say, Their Tenets which are <hi>most</hi> obnoxious to censure. There are many of your Tenets <hi>obnoxious</hi> to Censure, which you speak plain enough, about Perfection, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures not being the Word of God, or a Rule; also against the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> This is not <hi>fair</hi> dealing, but repeating your <hi>crimes,</hi> while you stand upon your <hi>Defence.</hi> And your inferences of their not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>certain</hi> of your Principles, from their calling your Expressions <hi>doubtful and unintelligible,</hi> forget that which you <hi>repeat</hi> of <hi>their words; scil.</hi> that they are <hi>usually</hi> so; which leaves room enough for your Expressions to be <hi>sometimes</hi> plain and <hi>intelligible.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60366:22"/>
               <p> And they can tell you (for all your <hi>Illogical Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs)</hi> how they come to know your <hi>meanings</hi> to be contradictory to your <hi>sayings:</hi> And that the <hi>Conscience</hi> of a Quaker (granting <hi>you</hi> to be <hi>one)</hi> is not to be named with that of a Presbyterian, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant, or of any sort of People who <hi>pretend</hi> to Christianity.</p>
               <p>But you are gotten into a <hi>vein</hi> of <hi>Self-applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Rhetorick, and seem to be so <hi>airy,</hi> as to believe your <hi>wortb</hi> to answer your <hi>words;</hi> it cannot possibly arise from any <hi>other</hi> cause (if you <hi>mean</hi> as you <hi>say)</hi> that you <hi>dare meet with them upon a publique Test,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ib.</note>
                  <hi>to prove your integrity to God and men.</hi> What a strange <hi>briskness</hi> and confidence have you attained to on a <hi>sudden,</hi> who to all the Solicitations, and Provocations you have received from <hi>me,</hi> to meet me in the Debate of Thirteen of the most horrid Principles I charge you with, have been as <hi>coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> as a <hi>Hare,</hi> and as <hi>cold</hi> as <hi>death? Canes timidi vehementius latrant quam mordent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it your Ignorance, Pride, Arrogance, or the <hi>lax</hi> your pen hath catcht? or is it all of them <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that makes you <hi>talk</hi> at this <hi>rate?</hi> or is it the courage you take from the consideration, that <hi>it may be, that One and twenty more of them cannot shew</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>age</hi> 15.</note>
                  <hi>so much wit as</hi> Ben. Johnson? which is a Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>yours,</hi> favouring more of <hi>Ben. Johnson's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical</hi> humour, than of either Wit, Modesty, or Honesty. Do you think your self a Match for One and twenty Divines, many a <hi>one</hi> of whom would think himself <hi>very idle</hi> to attend your <hi>wandring</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and shuffling <hi>tricks?</hi> But I suppose you know <hi>that</hi> as well as <hi>I can tell you,</hi> and that makes you talk <hi>without fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60366:22"/>
               <p> Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> I here tell you <hi>again,</hi> That I shall (if the Lord give me life and liberty) save them the trouble of contending with <hi>you,</hi> so far as <hi>proving</hi> what I have charged you with will amount unto. Or if you will, to make but <hi>one</hi> Question of it, and prove that <hi>you, and such as you,</hi> are no <hi>Christians.</hi> But I proceed.</p>
               <p>You say, <hi>And though you would have the people</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s. Rebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp;c.</hi> p. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>think very severe things of us, with respect to the Scriptures of truth; by telling them the Quakers hold, That the Scriptures are not the Word of God, nor a Rule of Faith and Practice; yea, that we readily assert it in so many words. I must tell you, you have acted with us herein far from men of common Ingenuity. A man might at this rate by Scripture prove,</hi> There is no God, <hi>if he would but leave out,</hi> The Fool hath said in his heart.</p>
               <p>But if this Charge of theirs (with others you as confidently <hi>contradict,</hi> and as vehemently <hi>decry)</hi> be proved <hi>true,</hi> and that out of your own <hi>Writings</hi> in your <hi>Defence;</hi> will it not be <hi>sadly implied,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> are the <hi>Fool</hi> that have said in <hi>your</hi> heart, <hi>There is no God?</hi> Certainly your carriage bespeaks you <hi>Atheum judicio;</hi> or at least, one who believes God seeth not, or regardeth not what you say or do? It is a most burthensom and nauseous thing, to have to do with a man, that will say any thing to slander and abuse his Antagonists and deny his own <hi>professed</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, rather than fail of <hi>that end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In your Answer to my Charge, That the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers deny the Scriptures of the Old and New-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament to be the Word of God; you say, <hi>I will</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ. to</hi> Faldo, <hi>p.</hi> 24.</note>
                  <hi>allow to him, without going any farther, that the People called Quakers, do deny the Scriptures to be the Word of God, and therefore shall take for granted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60366:23"/> what he quotes out of</hi> J. N. <hi>i. e.</hi> James Naylor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dare you say I have left out <hi>any</hi> thing of your <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence?</hi> I dare not <hi>promise</hi> you will not say, the most <hi>gross and wilful untruth;</hi> I am <hi>too</hi> well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with you, to have <hi>better</hi> thoughts of <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you flee to your <hi>owning</hi> in <hi>another place,</hi> That <hi>Christ</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> of God, and in <hi>that</hi> sence you deny the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be the <hi>Word</hi> of God, it will by no means <hi>help</hi> you: For the Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is about the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>those</hi> you perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily <hi>deny</hi> to be so in <hi>any</hi> sense. And for the <hi>Christ you own</hi> to be the <hi>Word</hi> of God, when all comes to <hi>all,</hi> it is but <hi>the Light within;</hi> as will appear by the next evidence I shall produce against you. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your own Friends (as you call them) may think of the matter, all wise-men will see you bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried under the ruines of your lofty Fabrick, built without the Foundation of Truth.</p>
               <p>I charged you in the Contents of my Fifth Chapter, with denying the Scriptures to be <hi>a Rule of Faith and Life:</hi> But <hi>you,</hi> after many words, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaker. no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chri.</hi> p. 65.</note>
                  <hi>nothing</hi> to the purpose, <hi>confirm</hi> my Charge <hi>thus</hi> stoutly, <hi>Wherefore, said the Prophet, Hear the</hi> Word <hi>of the Lord. What word?</hi> That <hi>nigh in the</hi> heart, <hi>which</hi> Moses <hi>and</hi> Paul <hi>preached. Still the</hi> outward <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s Answ.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faldo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 56.</note>
                  <hi>Instrument is not the Rule, much</hi> less <hi>are the</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, <hi>being they are but all</hi> external <hi>Instruments. And this I will</hi> abide by <hi>against all the insults of our Enemies (by God's assistance) that both they are</hi> but such <hi>Instruments, and that</hi> such <hi>Instruments are</hi> not <hi>the</hi> Gospel <hi>Rule; but that Light, Life, Power, or Spirit which useth them. And who attributes</hi> that <hi>honour to the</hi> Instruments, <hi>which is due to the chief Mover in it, or by it, commits</hi> downright <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60366:23"/>
               <p> Have you not here <hi>loaded</hi> them with a <hi>witness</hi> who take the Scriptures to be their <hi>Rule,</hi> by charging them to be <hi>no less</hi> than <hi>Idolaters for so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> What can you say or <hi>add</hi> to make the <hi>sence</hi> of your Expressions <hi>tolerable?</hi> You tell us indeed, that <hi>you believe and know they contain many godly</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb. &amp;c.</hi> p. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Rules.</hi> But will this mend the matter? I well remember, that one of your <hi>Prophets,</hi> who lived not long since (if not now) at the Peal in St. <hi>John-street,</hi> when I asked him, If that Text, <hi>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God,</hi> were <hi>obliging to me,</hi> having read it in the Bible? I could not perswade him to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P. M. W. H. M. F. W. W.</hi> &amp;c.</note>
                  <hi>acknowledg it,</hi> or that it was my duty to <hi>love God;</hi> he having before <hi>denied,</hi> that I was an <hi>inspired</hi> person. This was before divers witnesses, both Quakers and <hi>others,</hi> some of the first letters of whose names are in the Margin.</p>
               <p>It would be little for your <hi>Credit,</hi> that I should tell the World the <hi>occasion</hi> of that Conference, and how it <hi>issued.</hi> But it being <hi>a lewd practice</hi> (though pretended from your Principles) I shall forbear till it be farther called for, and conclude the present point with <hi>James Naylor</hi>'s testimony (whom you <note place="margin">Naylor<hi>'s Light of Christ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</note> own and honour <hi>still</hi> as none of your small Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) <hi>God is at</hi> liberty (saith he) <hi>to speak to his people by them</hi> [the Scriptures] <hi>if he please, and where they are given</hi> by Inspiration, <hi>he doth so. And so he is at</hi> liberty <hi>to speak by any other created thing, as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ. to</hi> Faldo<hi>'s Quaker. no Chri.</hi> p. 53.</note>
                  <hi>to</hi> Balaam <hi>by his Ass.</hi> These words of <hi>Naylor</hi> you <hi>own and justifie.</hi> Now let the World judg, whose <hi>ingenuity</hi> is to be <hi>preferred,</hi> yours, or those <hi>Worthies</hi> whom you have <hi>slandered?</hi> or, Whether <hi>your guilt</hi> is no better <hi>proved,</hi> than the Scriptures affirming, <hi>There is no God,</hi> by a disingenuous leaving out, <hi>The Fool hath said in his heart?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60366:24"/>
               <p> I find you in the <hi>next</hi> page, over-head and <hi>ears</hi> in your <hi>sportive-</hi>humour, upon the occasion of the phrase, <hi>Honey, or sweetness of Spirit,</hi> in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Epistle; which to make a <hi>gingle</hi> with, you turn into <hi>money</hi> by Interpretation: <hi>They [the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple]</hi> toil, <hi>and you</hi> talk; <hi>they are the</hi> Bees, <hi>and you, so many cunning Hivers; at the tinkling of whose bells the</hi> silly <hi>Bees assemble, and when you have safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hived them, your next business is to take their</hi> honey <hi>from them.</hi> Here you <hi>smite</hi> the <hi>standers by,</hi> instead of the men of your Controversie. As the <hi>Madman,</hi> Prov. 26. 18. you <hi>cast fire-brands,</hi> not at the <hi>Non,</hi> but <hi>Conformists,</hi> who only have the <hi>Bells</hi> to ring-in the Bees (as you call them:) But you care not <hi>whose</hi> head you <hi>break,</hi> so you may but <hi>break</hi> your <hi>jest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How they can say, that <hi>honest well-meaning souls</hi> may be <hi>judicially deserted of God,</hi> is not hard to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile;</hi> seeing they <hi>oppose</hi> them to <hi>you,</hi> and your <hi>crafty</hi> Leaders; they believing <hi>you,</hi> and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples they receive from you to be <hi>very good,</hi> while <hi>you</hi> (and many more of you) cannot but <hi>know</hi> that you <hi>delude.</hi> They follow you in the <hi>simplicity</hi> of their hearts, who (many of them) believe not that you hold what you do; and therefore hold not with you in <hi>many</hi> things. And the <hi>Ministers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue their word <hi>Honest,</hi> by <hi>well-meaning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Apology is more than their Expressions need; for when they speak of <hi>honest well-meaning souls,</hi> they say, <hi>Divers of them (so far as we can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Rebuk.</hi> p. 13.</note>
                  <hi>who are honest well-meaning souls.</hi> But in <hi>your Report,</hi> you leave out the whole Parenthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis, which abundantly <hi>alters</hi> the sence. And where you say, <hi>That Christians, while such, may be judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially deserted of God, and hived by the Devil: Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60366:24"/> such a contradiction beconceth not men of your stile and pretences.</hi> You take your <hi>own false</hi> conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>their</hi> words, and put it into a different letter as <hi>their words,</hi> that they may <hi>fall</hi> under the <hi>burthen</hi> which you <hi>treacherously</hi> create out of your <hi>own brain.</hi> Moreover, they say not <hi>absolutely,</hi> that they are <hi>deserted</hi> of God, but that they <hi>seem</hi> to be so. And so did <hi>Peter</hi> while he denied his Master.</p>
               <p>All this put together, renders you a <hi>habitual</hi> Falsifier in your <hi>Reports</hi> of your Adversaries <hi>words and sence;</hi> for were it not become <hi>natural</hi> to you, you would not be guilty of it in the very instant of accusing others for <hi>that</hi> crime.</p>
               <p>In the next place, I find you much offended, <note place="margin">Ib.</note> that they should so much as imply that there may be some <hi>Socianiz'd Persons, or Papists among you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the disguise of Quakers:</hi> And that is all that their <hi>words</hi> import. You affirm, That ye are neither <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> nor <hi>Papists;</hi> and require at their hands, to produce one Socinian, or Papist that goes under the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 13.</note>
                  <hi>name</hi> of a Quaker.</p>
               <p>If there be either Papists <hi>or</hi> Socinianiz'd persons among you, the suspicion they imply proves a <hi>truth.</hi> Although common Fame say, That you have had Jesuites, or Romish Priests, helping under your disguise, to promote the Quakers work, I shall not build upon that Foundation: But <hi>certainly,</hi> your Principles for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and your <hi>Resolves</hi> (as you call them) for <hi>Discipline,</hi> are so much of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Superstructure of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he that <hi>suspects not</hi> the hand of the Jesuite in the <hi>Plot,</hi> is very ignorant in either the Romish, or the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Principles.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60366:25"/>
               <p> I shall not repeat here what is done already in <hi>Quakerism no Christianity,</hi> Chap. 4. Sect. 6. and Chap. 12. Sect. 3. Thither I refer my Reader for farther satisfaction: These two Sections consisting of fourteen pages, being wholly taken up in the comparison of the Quakers and Papists, <hi>as such,</hi> in their Foundation and Doctrines. And for your <hi>Resolves</hi> for <hi>Discipline,</hi> I have printed it <hi>verbatim</hi> in my Appendix to the foresaid Book, with my parallel in your Order and Disciplines, as like al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most as two Eggs of the same <hi>Crow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I suppose you cannot be <hi>ignorant</hi> of the meeting of some of the <hi>chief</hi> Quakers and <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, designed</hi> for a Consult to save the Romish Priest <hi>lately</hi> convicted; which hath done your Cause <hi>so much</hi> service, as to <hi>confirm</hi> many in the belief, that you are rowing <hi>hard</hi> to <hi>Tybur.</hi> I can tell you the <hi>place</hi> of meeting, and <hi>names</hi> of the Consulters, and also what great and rich man among you, <hi>stormed</hi> sufficiently, that you made thereby the <hi>smoak</hi> of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicion to <hi>flame out</hi> into a clear evidence, that your <hi>Leaders</hi> and the Papists are <hi>Confederates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know <hi>also,</hi> who among your <hi>Great</hi> ones, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed</hi> the fact, but excused the <hi>guilt;</hi> by saying; that they were against the suffering of <hi>any</hi> upon the account of <hi>Religion,</hi> and did it upon that <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Principle. But let me tell you, that your <hi>chusing</hi> the Papists, rather than any other who are liable to sufferings by the Law, doth <hi>loudly</hi> prove, what I told you of in my former Book, of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manist's <hi>saying,</hi> being demanded, which of all the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaker, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hri.</hi> p. 54. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lt impr.</hi>
                  </note> Sects in <hi>England</hi> came <hi>nearest</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> he replied, <hi>The Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a <hi>Socianiz'd</hi> Person, I will seek no <hi>farther,</hi> when I find <hi>you;</hi> nor for other testimony than your
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60366:25"/> Book, entituled, <hi>Sandy Foundation shaken;</hi> where you make it the scope of your Book to deny, The <hi>Trinity</hi> of Persons in the <hi>Godhead,</hi> Justification by <hi>imputed</hi> Righteousness, <hi>Original</hi> sin, and the <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> of Christ for <hi>sinners.</hi> Though these <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Principles fill up the Volume of the Book, I will quote three of your Sentences: <hi>If God (as the Scriptures testifie) hath never been declared, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, but as the Holy</hi> One, <hi>then it will follow that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s San. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Found</hi> &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 12.</note>
                  <hi>God is not a</hi> Holy Three<hi>—Neither can this receive the least prejudice from that frequent, but impertinent distinction, That he is one in Substance, but three in Persons or Subsistences. The Second Person of the</hi> imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Page 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Title.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Trinity.</hi> So much for your denying the Trinity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Imputed</hi> Righteousness, and <hi>Original</hi> sin you deny in <hi>one</hi> breath thus: <hi>Because sin came not by</hi> Imputation, <hi>but</hi> actual <hi>Transgression—therefore must the Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 29.</note>
                  <hi>be as</hi> Personal <hi>for Acceptance.</hi> In denying Christ's <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> you go beyond the Socinians; for you say, <hi>Nor let any</hi> fancy, <hi>that Christ hath so fulfilled it</hi> [the Law] <hi>for them, as to exclude their obedience from being requisite to their Acceptance, but</hi> only <hi>for their patern.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id in Eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> p. 26.</note> Let this be added to your saying of Justification, and it will explain you. Is not here <hi>enough</hi> to render you not only <hi>Socianiz'd,</hi> but also a <hi>Socinian?</hi> If you say, the <hi>Socinians</hi> deny the <hi>Godhead</hi> of Christ, but so do <hi>not you:</hi> I answer, That if it were <hi>so,</hi> it would only render you not a <hi>compleat</hi> Socinian, but not <hi>clear</hi> you from being <hi>Socianiz'd.</hi> But let me tell you, that you <hi>deny</hi> the <hi>Godhead</hi> of Christ as well as they; for, they deny him to be God <hi>by Nature;</hi> and you affirm, the <hi>Light within</hi> (which is indeed but a <hi>natural</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, or Qualification) to be Christ, or God.</p>
               <p>So that the <hi>difference</hi> lies thus <hi>wide:</hi> The <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> will have Christ to be <hi>but a Creature;</hi> and you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60366:26"/> will have that which is <hi>but</hi> a Creature, <hi>to be Christ.</hi> Verily, they who call you <hi>Socinians,</hi> and stop there, do you a great deal of <hi>undeserved</hi> honour: For your Religion and Principles are made up of almost all Ancient Errours, with such a Superfetation, as if <hi>Quakerism</hi> were the <hi>sink</hi> into which they empty themselves, and the <hi>womb</hi> that brings them forth more monstrous than their Progenitors.</p>
               <p>I shall not be so idle and frivolous, as to give <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances</hi> of the Quakers ensnaring <hi>ignorant</hi> persons to <hi>their</hi> Principles, by the good opinion their <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosity</hi> in Garbs and Manners <hi>first</hi> obtained: For this were but to set up a Candle to mend <hi>Day-light.</hi> And that a Devotion to any pretended Religion, upon the consideration of mere <hi>outward</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, is Monkish, Nunnish, and Irrational, needs as <hi>little</hi> proof.</p>
               <p>If you think the <hi>little Bands, Cropt-locks, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>'s Reb. <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>c.</hi> p. 14.</note>
                  <hi>plain Apparel, severe Aspects</hi> of the Ancient Puritans, render them as <hi>obnoxious</hi> to Censure as the Quakers; you either know not them, or your selves. For that Garb was common in <hi>those</hi> days to men professing, or <hi>not</hi> professing the <hi>Puritanical</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; yea, <hi>generally</hi> used by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> even by <hi>those</hi> who were most <hi>Prelatical,</hi> and the <hi>keenest</hi> Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of the Puritans. Neither did they put <hi>so much</hi> of Religion into <hi>those</hi> Garbs, as to condemn such as were not so <hi>accoutred,</hi> for prophane and <hi>irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> persons; which is <hi>your</hi> case: There being none esteemed Quakers <hi>with you,</hi> who wear any <hi>Lace,</hi> or <hi>Ribbands,</hi> or that will salute by putting off the <hi>hat;</hi> or that will put <hi>I</hi> and <hi>No,</hi> in the room of <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay;</hi> or that will say <hi>You</hi> to a <hi>Single</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and not <hi>Thou.</hi> And your account of <hi>all</hi> that are not Quakers, is no better than <hi>Infidels, Heathen</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60366:26"/> (or <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> if professing the Christian Religion) <hi>out of the Life, and the Power.</hi> Phrases of <hi>yours,</hi> which by Interpretation import, ignorant of Christ, and Rebels to the Light, or no <hi>true Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>your Aspects,</hi> the name of <hi>Severe</hi> is much <hi>too</hi> good; for they are generally <hi>Supercilious, Elate, Sullen,</hi> or <hi>Wanton.</hi> The three first are <hi>every</hi> mans experiment that hath to do with you. And if you take the <hi>Wantonness</hi> of your <hi>Aspects sometimes,</hi> to be a <hi>slander;</hi> I need no <hi>other</hi> evidence to <hi>clear</hi> me, than the frequency of your Females (whether Maid, Wife, or Widow) when they meet their <hi>Men-friends,</hi> in the room of the <hi>more Civil</hi> Salutations, which you <hi>decry,</hi> taking them by the hands, or <hi>wrists,</hi> continuing a considerable space, <hi>wringing</hi> them <hi>hard,</hi> and looking <hi>stedfastly</hi> in each others faces, without one word speaking: And as they <hi>meet,</hi> so they <hi>part,</hi> having taken their <hi>fill</hi> of this ugly and <hi>bad-natur'd</hi> Ceremony.</p>
               <p>I doubt not but you will put a very good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction upon this <hi>uncivil</hi> Posture, as you attempt to do upon the <hi>worst</hi> the Quakers say or do: But when you have said <hi>all</hi> you can to <hi>excuse,</hi> it will be esteemed a <hi>wanton</hi> temptatious thing, and an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> from an <hi>ill Author,</hi> to destroy <hi>Modesty,</hi> and train you up to that Confidence and <hi>Fore-head</hi> your cause hath need of.</p>
               <p>I know you make a great noise about your <hi>suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> which you render so inseparable from a Quaker, that you give us the Construction of the <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> word to be, <hi>to expose themselves to the bitter Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema's of such High-Priests as your selves (the One and twenty</hi> Divines) <hi>the severity of their dearest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, the penalties of Magistracy, and to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reproach of the multitude.</hi> When you have said
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60366:27"/> thus much, you think you have said a great deal, to perswade people 'tis an <hi>inward</hi> Principle, and not outward <hi>appearance</hi> that prevails with persons to become Quakers. But what are all these suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings you mention, but in themselves <hi>outward</hi> appearances? And yet your often glorying of them, is mostly but hanging out a sign of the <hi>Goodness</hi> of your Principle, and thereby to draw in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selytes. But they who will take up in their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, where-ever they see the Sign of <hi>Sufferings</hi> at the <hi>door,</hi> may make a very ill <hi>choice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know you are not <hi>much</hi> afflicted with the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema's of the <hi>High-Priests</hi> (as you call them;) but if they should stir the <hi>old</hi> man, you can soon pay them in their own Coyn with <hi>interest,</hi> and avouch that kind of Retaliation to be from the <hi>Spirit,</hi> though from a very <hi>Revengeful</hi> one. For your <hi>other</hi> sufferings, paint them out in the bloodiest co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours you can devise, and I will produce you a Papist, a Jesuite, a Turk, a Heathen, who hath equalled you, or outdone you in the behalf of their <hi>Delusions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we set aside an <hi>erroneous Conscience,</hi> which may produce violent and preternatural <hi>heats,</hi> to act and <hi>suffer</hi> in the behalf of its false Sentiments; <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> teaches us, that men will maintain their more <hi>apparent</hi> Vices at a very costly rate. How many sacrifice their Health, Time, Parts, Estates, Wives, Children, Credit, and their Souls; and all for the gratifying those <hi>bruitish</hi> lusts of Drunkenness, Uncleanness, and other voluptuous Appetites! Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they more certainly know, <hi>those</hi> Iniquities will produce such ruines, than any of you are <hi>assured,</hi> that Quakerism will cost you any <hi>consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> losses?</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60366:27"/>
               <p> How many run the like hazards to please an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, malicious, or ambitious Humour? And I know not why Pride and Self-will (so predominant in most of you, and inseparable from your Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) may not engage you to adventure <hi>your share</hi> of sufferings, without any Religion concerned in the business, much-less the <hi>true</hi> Religion. What think you of your <hi>haughty</hi> Tenents, of having <hi>in you</hi> the Light which is <hi>infallible,</hi> the <hi>Power that hath all the Power of Heaven and Earth in it:</hi> That your <hi>Souls</hi> are not <hi>Creatures,</hi> but a <hi>part</hi> of God, <hi>infinite</hi> in themselves: That you are <hi>perfect,</hi> without any <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> of sin, so much as in your <hi>Natures:</hi> That you have <hi>somewhat,</hi> by which you are enabled, and <hi>priviledged</hi> to judg both persons and things: That all are Infidels, Ignoramuses, and Hypocrites (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting Spiritual and Religious things) excepting your <hi>selves:</hi> That you must shew <hi>honour</hi> and respect to <hi>no man,</hi> by the usual tokens of Hat, and Leg, or <hi>Sir,</hi> or any other Titles or Names of respect, except what is <hi>Relational:</hi> By which every <hi>Clown,</hi> and very <hi>mean</hi> person, who is a Quaker, mounts all on a sudden upon even ground (in this case) with Elders, Betters, Magistrates, yea the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; with whom he will go Cheek by Jole, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>apparency</hi> in his Deportment, that he is his inferiour?</p>
               <p>Would it not amaze a Reader to find your <hi>haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> opinion of your selves, and contempt of others, expressed in the following words? <hi>And here is the ground of all true Nobility, Gentility, MAJESTY,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Parnel <hi>Shield o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Truth,</hi> p. 25.</note>
                  <hi>Honour, Breeding, Manners, Courtesie, and Civility; no more after the flesh, but after the Spirit.</hi> A few lines after, he gives us the practical Improvement ye make of this <hi>Elate</hi> Principle: <hi>Who are not sprung
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60366:28"/> from the noble, gentle Seed; and to those honour is not due, neither can we bow unto them; for if we should, we should set the Devil in the room of God, and give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that which is due unto God.</hi> What do you <hi>conceit,</hi> according to the <hi>sence</hi> of these words (which never any of you disowned that I could hear or read, but the Book is owned by <hi>you,</hi> without <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,</hi> and its Author greatly praised:) Surely the <hi>sence</hi> of the words, without giving of <hi>Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences,</hi> is, That you conceit your selves to be Gods, and others of all sorts and ranks, to be but Devils. What a blasphemous Bait is here to a proud man to become a <hi>Quaker!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is become a <hi>Proverb,</hi> That not the Suffering, but the <hi>Cause</hi> makes the <hi>Martyr:</hi> Neither will the <hi>pretence</hi> of Conscience serve the turn, but a real good Conscience; which is a Conscience espousing Truth, and suffering for it in a righteous way. I have said the more upon <hi>this</hi> head, because I find that men espouse their Religion <hi>too often,</hi> upon the mere evidence of the sufferings of its Professors.</p>
               <p>In the next Paragraph your <hi>pen</hi> runs glib, while your <hi>Reason</hi> halts, and stumbles at your common rate. The one and twenty Divines say, as you repeat it. <q>And yet some of them being rich, and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reb.</hi> p 16.</note> growing into Estates in the World, can, and do live in as flesh-pleasing fulness, as others, whom they have condemned.</q> Now I shall repeat your Consequence, and leave it to the Reader to conclude, whose credit is in danger, your's or the Ministers. <hi>You say</hi> (say you) <hi>we condemn all but our selves. What is the Consequence but</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bid.</note>
                  <hi>this, if you speak true? That there is not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the World, that is not a professed Quaker, hath either more ability to live flesh-pleasing, or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60366:28"/> that actually doth indulge himself more to a sensual life, than some Quakers can, and do.</hi> By <hi>others,</hi> you will needs understand <hi>all</hi> others: By <hi>being rich,</hi> that there is not a person in the World of <hi>greater</hi> ability: By <hi>some of you,</hi> indulging to a sensual life as well as others, that no man lives <hi>more</hi> sensually than <hi>some</hi> of you. If you can <hi>wrest</hi> words at this rate, which are under your Readers <hi>eye;</hi> how much more, when the words you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue are out of their <hi>reach?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder (but why should I <hi>wonder</hi> at any thing you say) that you should <hi>tempt</hi> us to bring the names of your <hi>Grand-</hi>men on the <hi>stage,</hi> by your first Reply to the Ministers true Expressions; <hi>scil. I would willingly know</hi> (say you) <hi>these persons, who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                  <hi>they are? and where they live? Did you love the Truth, and your own Credit, ye would scarce be so lavishing of your words.</hi> Is there no <hi>flesh pleasing,</hi> but in a <hi>Ribband;</hi> or <hi>Lace,</hi> or <hi>Hat,</hi> or <hi>Congy?</hi> Are not your houses as <hi>stately,</hi> your meats and drinks as <hi>plentiful, various,</hi> and <hi>pallatable,</hi> your apparel as costly (Ribbands and Lace excepted) as some others whom you have <hi>condemned?</hi> Is this a matter hid in a <hi>corner,</hi> that we need to bring <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> instances for a proof? But if I must needs be at <hi>namely,</hi> Let your self (who ride in your Coach, and have your men following, and stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>bare</hi> to you, who live plentifully, and can bring out store of bottles of Wine for Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, bidding your Guests to use their freedom:) I say, let your self be one instance.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>John Osgood, William Mead, Roberts,</hi> be <hi>other</hi> instances; whose houses are large, furnished <hi>richly with Plate,</hi> and Tables with <hi>Provisions.</hi> I blame neither them nor you for living <hi>suitably</hi> to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60366:29"/> your Estates: But certainly, set those Bawbles of Ribbands, <hi>&amp;c. aside,</hi> you are not guilty of much self-denial in your bodily accommodations, which is a thing you so much pretend to above others.</p>
               <p>I had like to have let slip a passage of your <hi>Creed,</hi> which you <hi>bolt</hi> out, not very like the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Gospel;</hi> viz. <hi>And this I affirm, That all these</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge</hi> 15.</note>
                  <hi>endeavours many vigorously employ to vilifie an</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Principle, <hi>and disswade persons from believing</hi> in it, <hi>waiting upon it, and being guided by</hi> it, <hi>center in the</hi> rankest Atheism. How now Mr. <hi>Penn!</hi> Is this a time for you to profess faith in an <hi>inward</hi> Principle? Is it the <hi>truest Creed</hi> that renders <hi>Faith</hi> to be an <hi>inward</hi> Principle, and the <hi>Object</hi> to be <hi>without,</hi> and <hi>above</hi> us? or <hi>that</hi> which makes some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>within</hi> to be its <hi>Object.</hi> Farewel then the Jesus that <hi>died</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and all your disguising pretences of <hi>owning him;</hi> for surely he is not <hi>so far</hi> metamorphosed, as to become <hi>a Principle within you.</hi> What should we expect of a <hi>Leper,</hi> but the breakings out of his Disease, yea, when he is most deeply engaged in defending his <hi>cleanness?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, you say your <hi>pleasure</hi> of those words, wherein they <hi>recommend</hi> my Book; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>Wherein the Quakers Principles are more thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ebuke,</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 16.</note> investigated, than in any Book which we have seen. And we judg it for matter, proof, and stile, to be <hi>especially</hi> useful for those who need, or desire Information concerning the Quakers, and <hi>their</hi> Principles.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Upon these words you trumpet your <hi>Triumphs</hi> before the <hi>Battel,</hi> and would have it taken for <hi>granted</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> word, that the Divines have given <hi>you</hi> the <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt,</hi> and themselves the point of the sword at their own breasts: <hi>Had we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60366:29"/> no other Weapon</hi> (say you) <hi>this were enough to wound your cause incurably.</hi> But let us see what your <hi>Cockle-shel</hi> Triumph comes to. Your first is, <hi>He hath laid down about</hi> twenty <hi>Principles in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers name,</hi> eighteen <hi>of which are not only none of theirs, as so exprest, but not so much as by Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have <hi>said</hi> it, and that is <hi>all.</hi> You said <hi>near</hi> as much once <hi>before,</hi> and attempted the proof by <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 6.</note> only <hi>a single</hi> instance; wherein you so far <hi>failed,</hi> as not to give any Principle of <hi>yours,</hi> as it was laid down by <hi>me,</hi> but somewhat of your own in its stead; and as being <hi>conscious</hi> of your <hi>own guilt,</hi> you give neither Page nor Chapter where it might be found; which was as much as to say, if you would have me prove these to be his words, you may go look (for me) where to find them. But now, as if you suspected before the <hi>hard-hap</hi> your <hi>first</hi> attempt would meet with, you hide your head altogether, and suffer not one of the eighteen Principles (you say I have wronged you in charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you) to come into <hi>sight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I commend your prudence <hi>now,</hi> in leaving the proof to the mere Authority of your <hi>denial,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon those who will not afford it <hi>credence.</hi> But let us hear you: <hi>That they are none of ours, it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 17.</note>
                  <hi>is enough we</hi> say so, <hi>unless our Faith is not to be taken at</hi> our <hi>mouths, but at our</hi> Adversaries: <hi>He that tells me, I believe that which I do not believe, is either foolish or dishonest; and his Confutation is not of me, but of himself. That they are not our Principles by Consequence, I have abundantly proved, both in my</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid</note>
                  <hi>Answer and Rejoynder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what if this fine <hi>Harangue</hi> be proved both foolish and false, yea, and <hi>dishonest</hi> too; Have you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60366:30"/> not <hi>forfeited</hi> your credit? That your case is <hi>no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> I shall demonstrate so <hi>plainly,</hi> that common Reason and <hi>Sense</hi> will be my <hi>Compurgators.</hi> That your <hi>Faith is not</hi> (alway) <hi>to be taken at your own mouths</hi> is <hi>apparent;</hi> not only from your denying at <hi>one time</hi> what you profess vehemently at <hi>another</hi> (which I have already evinced) but also from your industrious <hi>hiding</hi> your Principles from such, who you <hi>believe</hi> will have no <hi>very good</hi> thoughts of them. What means that <hi>rude</hi> dealing of <hi>E. Burrough</hi> with the <hi>sober</hi> Querist, who desired to be informed from his <hi>own</hi> mouth, what his Principles were in these, and such-like Questions?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Whether the Word was made Flesh more, or <hi>oftner</hi> than <hi>once?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To this (instead of better Satisfaction) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urrough.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orks in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. <hi>p.</hi> 29, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> railing, and calls him <hi>Reprobate, Child of Darkness, of a dark polluted Mind, a stranger to the Life, without God in the World, the Light condemns thee, and all thy Generation eternally, thou art Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness it self, in the Sorcery and Witchcraft, thou Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, thou the Dragon, thou hast conjured up thy Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Black-Art, out of the Bottomless Pit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The second Query was <q>Whether did the <hi>man</hi> Christ slain (in respect of God's Decree and Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy) from the Foundation of the World, really and <hi>indeed</hi> suffer death, <hi>as</hi> upon the Cross at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> more or <hi>oftner</hi> than <hi>once?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Take his Reply to this entire (for the first I gave it you before, and therefore spared to repeat the whole) as follows: <hi>In this Query thou Diviner art</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d. in eod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 30.</note>
                  <hi>found adding to the Scriptures, the Divination of thine own brain, whereupon the plagues of God are to be added to thee, O thou Lyar! Where doth the Scriptures speak as thou speaks here? But in the Light thou art
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60366:30"/> seen, and art for the Condemnation. The man Christ we own, and witness, and the Lambs Book of Life, which was slain from the Foundation of the World: We witness the Lamb of God, and thee to be the Beast that makes war with the Lamb; and thou Antichrist, which looks at Christ's death at</hi> Jerusalem <hi>alone: So let all thy Congregation see what they hold up that follows thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What think you of this? have we not great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to expect an honest, <hi>plain</hi> account of your Principles at your <hi>own</hi> mouths, upon our most <hi>serious</hi> enquiry? Think not to put us off, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse this impertinent <hi>raving-</hi>way of Reply, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, That they are <hi>Trepanning Questions;</hi> for so you will call any that we are capable of framing for your discovery. I shall add no more of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> here; his Replies to the other Eighteen Questions are of the same make. And <hi>Burroughs</hi> (after all his <hi>Rant</hi> and Railing) concludes, <hi>Thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Burroug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Works in fol.</hi> p. 34.</note>
                  <hi>Queries are answered lovingly and plainly, and in the Scripture-Language and Terms; and with the eternal Light of God, set thee in thine own place, which thou shalt eternally witness.</hi> I believe my Reader will have no very good thoughts of your <hi>loving, plain</hi> Answers about your <hi>Principles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall now produce out of <hi>W. P</hi>'s own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, your <hi>great lothness</hi> to have your Tenets and way understood <hi>by us.</hi> You say upon the occasion <note place="margin">Penn<hi>'s Rejoynder to</hi> Faldo. <hi>p.</hi> 177.</note> of my obtaining your <hi>Resolves</hi> for Discipline, <hi>If such inoffensive, nay Christian and necessary Resolves for the right disciplining the Church of Christ in the ways of Peace and Righteousness,</hi> cannot escape <hi>John Faldo</hi>'s cruel hands, <hi>instead of rendering us</hi> Papists, <hi>I shall not wonder, if from a Non-conforming Priest, he turns a</hi> Spanish <hi>Inquisitor, or any thing else that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60366:31"/> can be worse.</hi> By this it <hi>appears,</hi> that for all the <hi>good</hi> Characters you give of your Resolves for Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, you would have them by all means <hi>escape my hands;</hi> and it grieves and angers you at the <hi>heart,</hi> that they cannot <hi>escape</hi> my <hi>Inquisition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Whitehead</hi> (as I have said before) could not with <hi>much</hi> importunity be brought to declare the Quakers Principle about the Resurrection of the dead. But at length he professed, <hi>He did not believe that his body should rise again.</hi> Yet this <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enn's <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nsw to</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldo, <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>00.</note>
                  <hi>extorted</hi> Confession you would have <hi>lick'd</hi> up <hi>again,</hi> and imply in your Answer to <hi>me,</hi> that it <hi>slipt</hi> out of his mouth at <hi>unawares.</hi> But to conclude, your great <hi>James Naylor</hi> hath sealed up your mouths, from an honest liberty to vent your minds to us, and that under a <hi>Curse: But the Mystery</hi> (saith he) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ames <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aylor</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e lost, <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note>
                  <hi>is sealed with the sons of God, nor can any ever know with what bodies they shall arise; but who comes to the</hi> flesh <hi>of Christ, and discerns his body, the sight whereof in the life slays the Serpent, and opens the</hi> Mystery. <hi>Till then,</hi> cursed <hi>is he that</hi> reveals <hi>that which God hath sealed up, and hidden from the</hi> Serpents <hi>wisdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I have abounded with <hi>evidence,</hi> that your Faith is not by <hi>us</hi> to be sought at your <hi>own</hi> mouths; and that it is neither foolish nor <hi>dishonest</hi> to tell you, that you do <hi>believe</hi> that which you say you do <hi>not</hi> believe, and that my Confutation is of <hi>you,</hi> not of my <hi>self.</hi> And if you ask me how I come to know your hearts, if not at <hi>your</hi> mouths? I let you know, that I have it especially from your <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings;</hi> which were designed either for your <hi>own</hi> party, or for such Ignorants among <hi>others,</hi> who finding the great words, <hi>The Light, Life, Power, Manifestations, Measures of Christ,</hi> &amp;c. think all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60366:31"/> the rest must needs be very <hi>good.</hi> And for all your <hi>Contradictions,</hi> I have in my <hi>Writings</hi> laid down your Principles in your <hi>own</hi> words; and aver <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> but what I give my ground for in the <hi>same</hi> words to a <hi>syllable,</hi> which I find in your <hi>owned</hi> Authors.</p>
               <p>I am now come to the <hi>main</hi> push; where <hi>you</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Reb.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> say, <hi>I will produce you ten Instances of notorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions, any one of which were unworthy of such poor Heathen as ye think us to be.</hi> I am very unwilling to tell you in <hi>plain</hi> terms, that you make no more Conscience of telling <hi>untruths,</hi> than the veriest <hi>Rake-hell,</hi> whose time is divided betwixt Cursing, Swearing, Drunkenness, and such <hi>reproachful Vices;</hi> or that your <hi>untruths</hi> have no <hi>cover</hi> but Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which renders your heart <hi>hardned</hi> from the <hi>fear</hi> of God. But if a <hi>virulent</hi> Accusation of your Adversary will condemn him, and clear you, the <hi>present</hi> day's your <hi>own,</hi> and we must languish till the Day of Judgment, under your <hi>unjust</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency. Yet, blessed be the Lord, my Integrity will find an evidence in <hi>your</hi> very <hi>Tests</hi> of my faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiness.</p>
               <p>I expected, after such <hi>huge</hi> Criminations, that when you came to <hi>proof</hi> and instances, somewhat would have been <hi>offered</hi> at <hi>(at least)</hi> to prove me an <hi>Irreverent Abuser of God, and the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. in eod.</hi> p. 8.</note> which you stoutly charged upon me; or that I had <hi>forged</hi> matters, and given them as <hi>your</hi> words, which yet were but my <hi>own invention.</hi> If you had found <hi>such a Crime</hi> in my Writings, it were as easie to be proved, as <hi>reading English.</hi> But behold, a few pretended Perversions, or false <hi>Consequences;</hi> all which will prove to be <hi>Will. P</hi>'s Perversions, and <hi>worse</hi> too. In the Vindication
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60366:32"/> of the Divines and my self from <hi>your</hi> Accusations, I shall distinguish <hi>your part</hi> from <hi>mine,</hi> by the titles of <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Accusation,</hi> and <hi>J. F</hi>'s. <hi>Vindication,</hi> and dispose of your Quotations and mine in the margin respectively.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="accusation">
               <head>1. <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOhn Faldo</hi> affirms, That <hi>W. Smith</hi> had not one <note place="margin">p. 17.</note> Exhortation to read the Scriptures. Nay, that the <hi>main</hi> design of the Book was to deny them, and <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k. no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rist. <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> throw <hi>dirt</hi> upon them; Yet <hi>J. F.</hi> cites him concerning the Scripture thus:</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                  <p>Then the Scriptures are to be owned and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y Answ. 42.</note>
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they are to be owned and believed, and they that do not so are to be denied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Observ.</speaker>
                  <p>Can any thing be more inconsistent than <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ejoynd. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 60, 61, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> your Reverend Author? Is it this sort of proof you commend? Can you think this the way to convert such Infidels as you deem us to be?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough I knew your <hi>Accusations</hi> to be <hi>false</hi> at <hi>first</hi> view, yet I little expected so <hi>careless</hi> a management of them by <hi>you;</hi> for the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective the <hi>cause</hi> it self is of honesty, the more <hi>need.</hi> it stands in of all other <hi>possible</hi> supports. But both in <hi>matter and manner</hi> you seem to be <hi>despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi> If it come to a Test, all your wit cannot make so <hi>bad</hi> a cause appear <hi>good:</hi> But if it never come to a tryal, it will <hi>pass,</hi> though in <hi>all</hi> respects <hi>very</hi> bad.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60366:32"/>
               <p> I consulted the Page and Book which your <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> directed me to, but the words are not <hi>there.</hi> I examined <hi>both</hi> Impressions, and also my <hi>VIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATION</hi> (supposing you might name one of my Books instead of <hi>another)</hi> and in <hi>page</hi> 45. of either of them, there are no such words. And indeed I know not where to find them; and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be supposed that I have all I write <hi>by rote.</hi> 'Tis an ill <hi>Omen</hi> of your <hi>success,</hi> to have such a <hi>flaw</hi> in your first attempt; and I might very fairly on this ground (if I had been guilty) have given you the <hi>go-by,</hi> and yet stood <hi>rectus in curia.</hi> But Truth needs no such <hi>shifts;</hi> I therefore say I do believe, that (for the substance) there are those words in some one of my Books, and I suppose in my <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Quakerism no Christianity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my Citation which you say is so inconsistent with those words, you <hi>direct</hi> your Reader to find it in your Answer, <hi>p.</hi> 42. which when look'd into, the Reader must seek somewhere else, or never find it. You direct also to your Rejoynder, <hi>p.</hi> 60, 61, 62. but you may assoon find it in your Almanack, as in any of these places, or in any of my Books: But had it been <hi>fair,</hi> if this troublesome fault had not been committed by you, to direct your Reader to <hi>your</hi> Books, and not my <hi>own,</hi> to see what I cited, and how consistent I was with my self? If my Arguments must be read with <hi>your Spectacles,</hi> to be sure they will be found very crack'd ones: And here as you have repeated my Citation, there is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable</hi> Treachery.</p>
               <p>After much <hi>search,</hi> I find the <hi>Citation</hi> not in any of my Books, but in a single <hi>open</hi> sheet, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A CƲRB FOR</hi> WILL. PENN'S <hi>CONFIDENCE,</hi> p. 3. which it may be did
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60366:33"/> so gall you, that you hated to repeat the very <hi>name</hi> of it. The Citation was of these words; Child. <hi>Then the Scriptures are to be owned and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved:</hi> (thus far you repeat my proof, but let drop <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>immer,</hi> 11.</note> all these following words in the Question, which explains the Answer) <hi>as a true Testimony of what the Saints were</hi> partakers of <hi>in</hi> that <hi>day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not here a large Thong cut out of my <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to make it too <hi>scanty</hi> for its end? What building can <hi>stand,</hi> if so much of the foundation be <hi>stoln</hi> away? But this only can do your work; and therefore you <hi>repeat</hi> the <hi>same</hi> crime in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to this Question: Father. <hi>Yes, they are to be owned and believed; and they that do not so, are to be denied:</hi> (Here you stop, and leave out these words following) <hi>But thou must take heed Child of giving more unto the Scripture, than unto them belongs, lest in so doing, thou diminish from the glory of Christ; (i. e.</hi> The Light within) <hi>and give it to another. And if thou lookest upon the Scripture to be for a Rule, and for trying, thou givest that unto them, which belongs to Christ; for he is the Rule, and leads his people, and he alone searches the heart, and tries the reins, and not the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> Whether are my <hi>Rationals,</hi> or your <hi>honesty</hi> of <hi>better</hi> proof? And to turn your Arrows upon your <hi>own</hi> head: Can any thing be more <hi>consistent?</hi> Is it <hi>this</hi> sort of proof which is to be condemned? It is this <hi>treacherous</hi> course you take to <hi>pervert</hi> persons <hi>into,</hi> and harden them <hi>in Infidelity.</hi> Moreover, these passages were not in the Book to which the Ministers affixt their Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle; and therefore your Accusation is as imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent <hi>as false.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60366:33"/>
               <p> Your passage of <hi>Smith</hi>'s of the service the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are of <hi>unto those that have received the same spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from whom they were given,</hi> is no more an Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to read them, than it is to <hi>attend to an Ass,</hi> according to <hi>Naylor before cited:</hi> For by the <hi>same Spirit,</hi> you intend no other than that <hi>Inspiration of the Spirit,</hi> by which the Prophets and Apostles received them. And if any thing be so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired, whether it be in the Scripture or not, 'tis all one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn's</hi> Accusation. 2.</head>
               <p>MY second Instance shall be this, that he maketh <hi>W. Smith</hi> call the Scriptures Traditions of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P</hi>'s. Rebu. <hi>p.</hi> 18. Quaker no Christ. <hi>p.</hi> 117, 119.</note> men, Earthly-root, Darkness, Confusion, Corruption, all out of the Life and Power of God; which he only ascribed to degenerated men, their Worship, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and Traditions. Shall this be called a Proof? doubtless a proof of nothing, but that hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful sort of Perversion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>
                  <hi>John Faldo's</hi> Vindication.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrst of all, I must tell you, that you</hi> abuse <hi>me, by making me to affirm that to be said of the Scriptures</hi> only, <hi>which I said was spoken of the Scriptures, and the</hi> Doctrines <hi>from thence</hi> received: <hi>And my words were these;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Of vilifying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the</hi> Scriptures, <hi>and the</hi> Doctrines <hi>from</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quaker. no Chr. <hi>p.</hi> 119.</note>
                     <hi>thence</hi> received.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may remember, that in my</hi> VINDICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, <hi>&amp;c. to which you</hi> rejoyned, <hi>I told you</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vindicat. of Quak. no Chri. <hi>p.</hi> 45.</note>
                  <hi>concerning this very Accusation,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That if</hi> Penn <hi>dare give me a meeting with</hi> impartial <hi>Judges, I
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60366:34"/> will (if God permit) produce the Book, and prove it to his face.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <hi>But this offer you never</hi> yet <hi>accepted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet, for my Readers satisfaction, I shall give him this large account in the words of the Quaker-Author whom you would vindicate.</hi> But who <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atch, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 16.</note> knows not him to be come that is true, they are not in the Saints life: So runs into their words, and gets their words, and sows them together, and makes themselves coverings; but abides in the Darkness, and brings forth that which is false, then searches the Scripture for words to prove their Image a lawful Son: And this is the bottom and foundation of all Religions this day, centring in the Letter, and running thither for shelter; but are all from the Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And knows not the Life of <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prophets, and the Apostles; but stands clothed and decked with <hi>their words,</hi> and there seem to be something, and to stand above others in their shew of godliness, and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worship, but knows not the <hi>Life revealed:</hi> So their <note place="margin">Id. <hi>p</hi> 21.</note> strength lies in the <hi>Letter,</hi> and what the Saints have declared, who were in the Power of God redeemed.—And this is but the same which all will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in words, and differs nothing in the ground from the Faith of those they are separated from; but branches forth of the same root, and all their practice springs out of the same ground, and is the Harlots Child, though dressed with a fairer covering.</p>
               <p>And what was by the Saints given forth, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <hi>in Writing without</hi> them, that their <hi>life is in,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> they contend about: And all strives to set <note place="margin">Id. <hi>p.</hi> 22, 23</note> up their own Conceivings, and teach for Doctrines <hi>mens Traditions;</hi> and mind not the measure of God <hi>in themselves,</hi> but stretch beyond it in the Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, and run into other mens lines and labours,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60366:34"/> and are all upon the earthly root, and in Darkness and Confusion in their Practice and Worship.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To this is added in the same page, and applied, all those execrable Names which I repeated in</hi> QƲAKERISM NO CHRISTIANITY.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Conclusion of this part of his Book begins thus:</hi> So all watch to the morning, that the day may <note place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</note> break upon you, and the Light shine out of Darkness <hi>in you,</hi> that your eye may look into the glass of Righteousness, the pure Light of Christ <hi>in</hi> your <hi>own</hi> Consciences. <hi>I shall add but one instance more out of the same Book, which will render my Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> down-weight.</p>
               <p>So amongst the words you find how the Saints in some things walked, and what they practised; and then you strive to <hi>make</hi> that thing to your selves, and to <hi>observe</hi> it, and <hi>do</hi> it, as near as you <hi>can.</hi> And <note place="margin">Morning-Watch, <hi>p.</hi> 45.</note> here you are found Transgressors of the just Law of God, which saith, <hi>Thou shalt not make to thy self any graven Image, nor the likeness of any thing.</hi> Now what <hi>difference</hi> is there in the <hi>ground</hi> betwixt you and the <hi>Pope,</hi> though in the appearance there seem so great a space?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By these Citations you may observe, that his</hi> scope <hi>is to decry the Scriptures as our</hi> Rule, <hi>and what</hi> Doctrines <hi>have their foundation</hi> in them. <hi>Charging those with</hi> Idolatry, <hi>who set up the Scriptures as their</hi> Rule; <hi>pretending that it is a placing them in the room of the</hi> Light within: <hi>And although he allows a</hi> great <hi>difference between us and the Pope, yet we come all under the</hi> same Condemnation, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we are the same in the ground of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession (as he speaks) which is, a not-being-guided by the Inspirations of the Light</hi> within, <hi>but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending (at least) to the</hi> Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="accusation">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60366:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation. 3.</head>
               <p>THat the Quakers understand by knowledg ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the flesh, the use of the understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uaker. no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hri. <hi>p.</hi> 41.</note> though sanctified, which is also a gross abuse both of our words and sense.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe would think that so <hi>thundering</hi> a Charge as <hi>W. P</hi>'s, would have produced out of so many <hi>thousand passages</hi> as were in my Book, <hi>far greater</hi> crimes than these <hi>ten</hi> you have pitched on; some of which are about your <hi>meanings</hi> of words. And no man will doubt, but that you were <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved</hi> (in such a Piece as yours) to detect the worst of mine. Herein you highly <hi>commend</hi> my Book, whose Reports of my travels into your <hi>so unknown a Land,</hi> shall be guilty of no greater mistakes. Yet those you pretend to be such <hi>gross</hi> ones, will be proved <hi>none</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>You your self call the understanding of such who are <hi>unregenerate</hi> (in your sense) <hi>a ravening Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Sp. of Tru.</hi> p. 23.</note>
                  <hi>Brain—fleshly Comprehensions.</hi> But who are your <hi>unregenerate</hi> persons? Verily all such as give not themselves up to the conduct of the <hi>Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;</hi> or in <hi>your</hi> words, who do not <hi>come into the daily obedience of the Light, and there rest contented to know only as they experience.</hi> Now unless you can <hi>prove,</hi> that <hi>no</hi> man's understanding, except a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers or Enthusiasts, is <hi>sanctified,</hi> you intend <hi>their</hi> understandings to be <hi>fleshly</hi> understandings, which yet are <hi>really sanctified:</hi> For many have their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings sanctified, who are neither Quakers nor Enthusiasts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="accusation">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60366:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation. 4.</head>
               <p>THat 1. <hi>Pennington</hi> should call visible Worship, <note place="margin">Vindic: <hi>p.</hi> 50.</note> as such, the City of Abomination. This is a down-right Forgery, and your praise of his proofs makes you Accessaries, look on it as you will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt those worthy Divines look on it as they ought, and will; that is, <hi>compare</hi> your Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation with the Book and page you <hi>quote,</hi> and they will find <hi>you the Forger,</hi> even in <hi>those</hi> words where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you pretend <hi>me</hi> to be guilty of <hi>Forgery.</hi> If you can find the words <hi>Visible Worship, as such,</hi> among <hi>my</hi> words, I will never trust my eyes more. There are indeed <hi>those words</hi> in the <hi>next</hi> page, but they are <hi>your</hi> words which I cited out of your answer, and not <hi>mine.</hi> But if I were to make <hi>proof</hi> that you hold <hi>visible</hi> Worship (as <hi>such)</hi> to be an <hi>error,</hi> your admired <hi>George Fox</hi> would bring me off <hi>clear;</hi> for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox. Myst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 65.</note> he saith, Paul <hi>brought the Saints off from the things that are seen, and Water is seen and its Baptism.</hi> Now if things that are <hi>seen,</hi> are not <hi>visible,</hi> I have <hi>fail'd;</hi> if they <hi>are, Fox</hi> saith, that <hi>Paul</hi> brought the Saints off from <hi>them,</hi> and by Consequence from Baptism by water.</p>
               <p>Indeed such virulent fashoods, and confident slanders being made <hi>apparent,</hi> will very much <hi>praise</hi> the Book, but much more <hi>dispraise you.</hi> Look on it how you will, God and good men will abhor your doings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="accusation">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60366:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation. 5.</head>
               <p>THat by Traditions of men, we understand the Scriptures, or written Word; a base abuse of our <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aker. Christ. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rt</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi>
                  </note> words!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat I said, I will prove out of the Writings of <hi>W. Smith: Have you felt his Power</hi> (saith he) <hi>to take away your sin? If yea, then why do you</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orning-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atch,</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>teach for Doctrines</hi> mens Traditions? <hi>and build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other mens</hi> Labours, <hi>and stretch your selves beyond your own Measures, running into the Lines of what others have written?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Although all that are acquainted with the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers phrasifying,</hi> will no more question the words <hi>Traditions of men,</hi> in this place, to be understood of the Writings of the Pen-men of the Scripture, than that two and two make <hi>four:</hi> Yet I shall give farther evidence of it, out of your <hi>own</hi> words; <hi>viz. Whereas</hi> J. F. <hi>runs back two or three thousand years</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ynder to</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aldo, <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>65.</note> a pilferring <hi>for his Hackney Sermons, out of them</hi> [the Prophets <hi>words] which are so well known to be other mens lines and labours. Smith</hi> explains <hi>mens Traditions,</hi> by other mens <hi>Labours, and Lines, and Writings:</hi> And you tell us, that the Prophets words (and a little after the Bible) are <hi>other mens Lines, and Labours.</hi> But if we consider this pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of <hi>mens Traditions,</hi> &amp;c. to be out of the same Book and Author, from whom I quoted such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous passages against the <hi>written</hi> Word upon my Second Vindication a little before, there will be no room left for doubting to the Intelligent,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60366:36"/> though they are unlearned in the Quakers <hi>double</hi> Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn's</hi> Accusation. 6.</head>
               <p>THat the Quakers mean by the Veil that is over <note place="margin">Quaker. Chr. <hi>p.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> people, their belief of the man Christ Jesus, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> to be now existing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. An Impiety of his own inventing, and your approving!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s</hi> Vindication.</head>
               <p>YOu are still in the <hi>meanings</hi> of words, which if I should have <hi>mistaken,</hi> were no <hi>great</hi> Crime, seeing we have no <hi>Dictionary</hi> wherein you <hi>expresly</hi> tell us, what the meanings of your <hi>new-coyn'd</hi> phrases, and <hi>new-</hi>meanings of <hi>old</hi> ones are. But it seems I am as able to make one as any of you, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of about three hundred words and phrases of <hi>yours,</hi> which had <hi>peculiar</hi> meanings of your <hi>own,</hi> whose meanings I gave, your <hi>chief</hi> Objections are against these <hi>three,</hi> and yet without <hi>cause.</hi> Why did you not charge me here with <hi>forging</hi> words, and fathering them upon <hi>you?</hi> or pretending those Citations of <hi>mine</hi> to be in <hi>your</hi> Books, which were <hi>not</hi> there? This had been of some <hi>weight,</hi> and easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discovered. But this you <hi>dare not attempt, and without</hi> it <hi>all</hi> my Charges stand <hi>firm;</hi> and I have <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb. &amp;c.</hi> p. 6.</note>
                  <hi>your word for it,</hi> who say, <hi>Since the strength of the Book depends upon Testimonies out of</hi> our <hi>Writings.</hi> But seeing I must combate your trifling Forces, or you will brag of the Victory, I shall clear my self of the falsity of this meaning <hi>also.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60366:37"/>
               <p> I have found the meaning I gave of, <hi>The Veil is over them;</hi> and have also <hi>found you</hi> very <hi>unfaithful</hi> in your <hi>report</hi> of it. I beg of my Reader to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our <hi>Reports</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> and all others which are within his <hi>reach,</hi> that he may be able to determine on whose part <hi>faithfulness</hi> lies. My words are these to a <hi>syllable:</hi>
                  <q>The belief of the man Christ <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ak. no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r. impr.</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. p. 324.</note> Jesus, which was of our nature, to be the Christ; and now existing in Heaven, in that body of flesh of our Nature, which he took of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus was I <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>word</hi> it, to express the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Nature of the <hi>true</hi> Christ, <hi>distinctly</hi> from your <hi>fallacies:</hi> For you <hi>fancy</hi> a man Christ Jesus, flesh, blood, and bones to be <hi>in you;</hi> yea, and who was born of the Virgin; yea, that <hi>Heaven</hi> is <hi>within</hi> you; and so <hi>your</hi> man Christ in <hi>your</hi> Heaven, is quite another thing than <hi>ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the meaning I gave is <hi>genuine,</hi> your <hi>own</hi> words shall prove, The phrase you deny not; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Penn<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ejoynder</hi> Faldo, 309.</note> (say you) <hi>the Apostle</hi> Paul <hi>desired not thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to know Christ after the flesh, but spiritually as he was the Son of God revealed in himself.</hi> It is but a mere <hi>blind,</hi> for you to construe this saying of <hi>yours</hi> to intend a <hi>fleshly</hi> knowledg, for that is the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Faculty, or its Act; for you intend it of the flesh, or <hi>body</hi> of Christ as the <hi>Object.</hi> And you bring in this Argument, among others, to back a saying of <hi>J. Pennington's,</hi> and another of <hi>yours;</hi> which were these, <hi>This we certainly know, and can</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>'s Rejoy.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faldo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 296.</note>
                  <hi>never call the bodily Garment Christ, but that which appeared and dwelt in the body.</hi> This is <hi>Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's.</hi> But say you, <hi>In short, Christ qualified that</hi> body <hi>for his service, but</hi> that body <hi>did not constitute</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d in eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 300.</note>
                  <hi>Christ. He is invisible, and</hi> ever was <hi>so to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly World.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60366:37"/>
               <p> All this I produce, to give <hi>light</hi> to <hi>your</hi> sense, in what I shall produce farther out of the <hi>same</hi> Chapter, and relating to the <hi>same subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In your <hi>seventh</hi> Reason, <hi>So must all know a death</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>to their</hi> fleshly <hi>ways, and</hi> Religion, <hi>yea, their knowledg of Christ himself after the</hi> flesh, <hi>or they</hi> stick in the veil. You proceed in your eighth Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>And these who at this day do</hi> feed <hi>upon the history of the</hi> bodily <hi>appearance (yet honourable in its place) and know not a breaking through the</hi> veil <hi>by witnessing a measure of the same Divine Wisdom, Power, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, Grace and Truth, revealed and born forth in themselves, they are but</hi> carnal and fleshly <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi> Here is enough and to spare for the proof of the meaning I gave of your phrase, <hi>The veil is over them.</hi> I shall be shorter in the rest.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn's</hi> Accusation. 7.</head>
               <p>FRom <hi>W. Smith</hi>'s saying, That the present pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice <note place="margin">Quaker. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Christian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 163.</note> of the Sacraments, as baptizing with a Cross, and counting the Bread and Wine the Flesh and Blood of Christ, arise from the Popes invention; you in the person of <hi>John Faldo</hi> give out, that <hi>W. Smith</hi> calls the Lords Supper the Popes invention. At this rate, what will your testimony be worth? Little cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, with such as know good Coyn from bad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo's <hi>Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF what <hi>you</hi> here report <hi>Smith</hi> to say be <hi>scanned,</hi> neither <hi>he</hi> nor <hi>you</hi> can be <hi>guiltless;</hi> for there is not a greater opposition in <hi>any</hi> thing betwixt the Pope and <hi>us,</hi> than about the <hi>sence</hi> of the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament being the Body and Blood
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60366:38"/> of Christ. But what you say; <hi>scil.</hi> That I <hi>conclude</hi> that <hi>W. Smith</hi> calls them the <hi>Popes Invention</hi> from the <hi>words you offer,</hi> is a great untruth: For first, I do not cite divers of them. And secondly, <hi>Smith</hi> saith in so many words, <hi>They arose from the Popes Invention.</hi> And for my Readers satisfaction, I will recite him out of his own Book, where I quoted him: And it will appear, that he said it of both the <hi>matter,</hi> and <hi>our use</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Child. <hi>I would fain know how it is concerning</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>immer,</hi> 163.</note>
                  <hi>those things called Ordinances; as, Baptism, and Bread and Wine, which are mucb used in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Father. <hi>Why Child, as to those things, they rose from the</hi> Popes Invention, <hi>who hath had power in the night of Apostacy, and hath set up his devices, which are yet continued in</hi> England. Where was your <hi>fear of God</hi> when you wrote this <hi>slander?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation. 8.</head>
               <p>FRom <hi>Edw. Burrough's</hi> making the Light <hi>of</hi> Christ <hi>within</hi> to be <hi>one in nature</hi> with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Christ; <hi>J. Faldo</hi> infers, That the Quakers hold the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>indicat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 75. to <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note>
                  <hi>Soul</hi> to be God: As if that had been said of the Soul, which was said of the Light <hi>of</hi> Christ shining <hi>in</hi> the Soul, or that they were Synonimous. What cannot a man of skill in this <hi>Black-Art</hi> do? yet this is your own Reverend Author, who for his proof against the Quakers, is not a little in your Books.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60366:38"/>
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is as <hi>like</hi> the <hi>rest</hi> of your <hi>slanders,</hi> as the Child of <hi>their</hi> Father. You make my Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from <hi>Burrough</hi>'s words to take up 12 <hi>pages.</hi> In looking for matter relating to <hi>Burrough's words,</hi> according to <hi>your Quotation,</hi> I almost <hi>despaired</hi> of finding <hi>any:</hi> At length I found somewhat in <hi>p.</hi> 80. and <hi>all</hi> I said to it, took up <hi>not</hi> eight lines. And you leave out a material part of the Citation (for you use not to be guilty of but one fault;) <hi>viz. Even as good as the Spirit of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall give a better, and <hi>truer</hi> account of my <hi>reasoning,</hi> which will prove you an unworthy <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer: Burrough</hi>'s words, as cited, and as <hi>you recite</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ to</hi> Faldo, <hi>p.</hi> 194.</note> them in your <hi>Answer,</hi> were these to a <hi>letter: Every man has that which is one in union, and like the Spirit of Christ; even</hi> as good <hi>as the</hi> Spirit <hi>of Christ, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its measure.</hi> Now I will repeat my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion both from <hi>Burrough</hi>'s words and <hi>yours</hi> in my <hi>VINDICATION,</hi> which your Quotation saith took up twelve pages: <q>If (said I) what <note place="margin">Fald. <hi>Vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> of Quak. no Christ.</hi> p. 86.</note> every man has, be <hi>as good in kind as the Spirit of Christ</hi> (which he <hi>[Pen]</hi> confesseth) it must be God; for there is nothing <hi>so good</hi> in <hi>kind</hi> as the Spirit of Christ, which is God, but God himself.</q> But by its <hi>measure, Penn</hi> will have, 'Tis as <hi>good,</hi> but not so <hi>great,</hi> or <hi>so much</hi> as the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>Here is not a <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Light of Christ</hi> in my <hi>Citation,</hi> nor of the <hi>Soul</hi> in my <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether yours or <hi>mine</hi> be the <hi>Black-Art,</hi> let all <hi>sober</hi> men judg. It is not such revilings, and <hi>weak</hi> (though <hi>Confident)</hi> slanders, will make those Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60366:39"/> Divines you <hi>traduce</hi> and <hi>scorn,</hi> ashamed to own their Author's <hi>proofs</hi> against <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn's</hi> Accusation. 9.</head>
               <p>BEcause <hi>G. F.</hi> rejected that <hi>Carnal</hi> Notion, that <note place="margin">Quak. no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrist. <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 10.</note> confines the Infinite, Omnipresent God, to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidence only above the Stars; he makes no difficulty of inferring, That we deny the Humane nature of Christ. As absurd as base!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo's <hi>Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Find you as <hi>tardy</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> as any man can wish, who must prove you a Deluder, or abide under the <hi>burthen</hi> you load <hi>me</hi> withal. There is not one word of the <hi>Humane Nature</hi> of Christ in both those pages; nor do I <hi>attempt</hi> to prove your <hi>denying</hi> it, till <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. which is near 200 pages <hi>off.</hi> I find indeed these words of <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s, cited <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Your imagined God beyond the Stars.</hi> But I infer from thence in that place, <hi>your Blasphemy,</hi> and that is all. And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. I have produced <hi>such,</hi> and <hi>so many</hi> proofs of your denying the Humane Nature of Christ, as you will never <hi>clear</hi> your selves of, till you <hi>repent,</hi> and change your <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="accusation">
               <head>
                  <hi>William Penn</hi>'s Accusation. 10.</head>
               <p>FRom our affirming, that such a kind of reading of <note place="margin">Quak. no Christ. <hi>p.</hi> 190.</note> Scriptures as the Pharisees used, and to those ends, makes men harder to be wrought on to true Conversion, than the Heathen: <hi>John Faldo</hi> infers, That reading the Scriptures, and getting knowledg thence, puts men into a worse condition than the Heathen; and that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60366:39"/> there is scarcely any thing more dangerous, than read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture. Yea, he accuses us of charging the miscarriages of mens souls on the knowledg the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by God's blessing doth convey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>John Faldo<hi>'s Vindication.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have sought for the <hi>matter</hi> of your Charge where <hi>you</hi> direct me: But in the first Impression there is no page signed with 190, because the figures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the several parts. In the last Impression, <hi>page</hi> 190 I find, but no more of the <hi>matter</hi> you <hi>charge</hi> me with, than is on the <hi>back-side</hi> of the <hi>Book.</hi> Do you not by such <hi>shifts</hi> as these, design to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row your Falshoods from <hi>Discovery;</hi> and to tire me with following an<hi>—used to the Wilderness?</hi> I greatly suspect it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>I might fairly upon these accounts have declined farther notice of many of your Charges but Truth and Evidence takes pleasure in a Tryal. After <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaker. no Chr.</hi> impr. <hi>ult.</hi> p. 102.</note> much search, I find <hi>somewhat</hi> of it in my ninth Chapter. Let us now <hi>compare</hi> notes, and behold <hi>your</hi> Justice.</p>
               <p>What I inferr'd, was from these words; <hi>Making him wise and able there [in his head] to oppose Truth, and so bringing him into a state of Condemnation, Wrath, and Misery beyond the Heathen; and making him harder to be wrought upon by the Light and Power of Truth, than the very Heathen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But will not your Reader think you out of your <hi>honesty,</hi> or me out of my <hi>wits,</hi> in reading what you say I infer from the Quakers words? viz. <hi>That read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, and getting knowledg thence, puts men into a condition worse than the Heathen,</hi> &amp;c. No such matter: But I conclude, If it be so as the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60366:40"/> Quaker-Author saith, then I scarce know what is more <hi>dangerous</hi> than reading the Scripture; and this is <hi>every</hi> word of <hi>my</hi> Conclusion.</p>
               <p>But suppose I should take <hi>your</hi> word, that the Quaker spake it of reading the Scriptures as the Pharisees <hi>us'd,</hi> and to <hi>those</hi> ends; What shelter from the storm will it afford you? This is but a <hi>common trick</hi> you have to <hi>hide your</hi> sence from the Reader, unacquainted with <hi>your</hi> sence of <hi>your</hi> words; for all that you <hi>intend</hi> by it, is but such a reading as depends not upon Apostolical <hi>Inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or rather the Conduct of <hi>your Light within.</hi> And <hi>so</hi> we all read as the Pharisees <hi>us'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet that I may not make an <hi>empty</hi> sound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>proof</hi> of its truth, I will demonstrate out of the most Learned Author that ever was yet a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, how <hi>you</hi> understand the <hi>manner and ends</hi> of the Scribes, or Pharisees (which are all one in the case) <hi>reading</hi> the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> (saith he) <hi>to</hi> such <hi>wise Sayers and Knowers</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fisher Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ata quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dam Rev.</hi> p. 6.</note>
                  <hi>as these (and such were the</hi> Scribes) <hi>who were</hi> ever scraping <hi>in the</hi> Scriptures <hi>to find God and his Life, yet never knew him at any time, nor saw his</hi> shape, <hi>because they heard not his voyce, nor heeded his Word</hi> in themselves, <hi>John</hi> 5. 37.] What think <hi>you,</hi> or rather what will my <hi>Reader</hi> think of <hi>this?</hi> For the manner and frequency of reading the Scriptures as the Scribes, is to be <hi>ever</hi> scraping <hi>in the Scriptures.</hi> A most scornful phrase! Their ends were <hi>to find God and his Life:</hi> Is this the end that makes read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them so mischievous? But the Reason he gives why they missed of their end is, <hi>because they heard not his voyce, nor heeded his Word in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;</hi> that is, they heeded not <hi>your</hi> Christ, <hi>the Light within.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60366:40"/>
               <p> Now if you allow <hi>Fisher</hi>'s Explanation of the Scribes or Pharisees reading the Scriptures (which you dare no more to contradict, in so many words, than the Bible) you your self affirm, that <hi>our</hi> read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures makes <hi>us harder to be wrought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to true Conversion than the Heathen.</hi> And it is o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>mercy</hi> that they <hi>do so,</hi> if we take <hi>true Conversion</hi> in your sense; for they preserve us (by the <hi>Grace</hi> of God) from turning <hi>QƲAKERS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now let the <hi>sober</hi> Reader judg, if <hi>my infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> be not as clear as <hi>Sun-beams,</hi> and somewhat <hi>illustrated</hi> by what <hi>you say</hi> to mend your sence. Thus by the good-hand of the Lord upon me, I have wiped off all the <hi>dirt</hi> your utmost virulency and <hi>cunning</hi> could throw upon my <hi>Book,</hi> and thereby upon those Reverend Divines for their <hi>Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>Let us now see what bold Reflections you make from such a heap of <hi>bold Ʋntruths</hi> and Forgeries. <hi>Behold</hi> (say you) <hi>at what a rate your Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Rebuk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> p. 19.</note>
                  <hi>hath investigated our Principles! you have said truly, in saying he did it throughly; for he hath scarcely touch'd any thing, that he hath not throughly abused: Yet this is the man whose attempts, so obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as you see, you have adventured to commend. You say, you judg it (among other things) for the PROOF of it, to be especially useful for those who desire infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation concerning the Quakers, and their Principles. That ever men of your Age, Experience and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, should precipitate themselves into any thing so foul and scandalous: Can you believe this is imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, and being just to the Quakers? I hope your condition is not yet so dangerous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have you your <hi>Peer</hi> for Confidence, and <hi>no Conscience,</hi> who can reflect in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60366:41"/> upon so many persons of <hi>Worth and Integrity,</hi> from the slanders and <hi>untruths</hi> of your <hi>own</hi> devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing? Certainly you have hereby <hi>deserved</hi> to be <hi>remark'd</hi> for the most <hi>abusive</hi> Impostor that hath pretended to <hi>Christianity.</hi> At this rate you manage your Controversie against <hi>me</hi> in all your Writings. I doubt not but all judicious men will take your <hi>behaviour</hi> to be a sufficient discharge to <hi>me,</hi> or any <hi>other,</hi> from considering or <hi>regarding</hi> what <hi>you</hi> say or <hi>write.</hi> You take a course not only to <hi>destroy</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>true</hi> Principles, but all <hi>civil</hi> Converse: For if the highest Pretences and <hi>Protestations</hi> of Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, shall be found but the cover of <hi>Falseness;</hi> and Truth and Honesty trampled under foot by <hi>those</hi> who clothe their Assertions with <hi>them, whom</hi> shall we <hi>believe?</hi> to <hi>what</hi> shall we <hi>trust?</hi> The Lord <hi>discover</hi> both you, and your Principles, whose <hi>hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Properties, need such kind of falsities for their <hi>Refuge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are pleased to tell me (according to the <note place="margin">P's <hi>Reb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 22.</note>
                  <hi>usual violence</hi> of your phrasifying) that I most <hi>horribly</hi> abuse you, in saying, you pretend <hi>all</hi> your <hi>Ministers</hi> to be <hi>infallible:</hi> And you <hi>explicate</hi> your self thus, <hi>We ascribe not an infallibility to men, but to the Grace of God; and to men, so far as they are led by it; for that it certainly teacheth what it doth teach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if this Charge against you be <hi>true,</hi> and your <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Answ.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 36, 43.</note> Defence but a shuffle; have you not <hi>horribly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicated?</hi> How often have you scornfully thrown in my teeth, <hi>This is your fallible, errable</hi> John Faldo! <hi>This fallible, errable Priest!</hi> Did you intend this of my <hi>person,</hi> or not? Surely you intended it of the <hi>man John Faldo.</hi> But if you ascribe not Infallibity to <hi>any</hi> man, why do you make my <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> my <hi>Reproach?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60366:41"/>
               <p> Let us hear your greatest <hi>Oracle</hi> in the case: <hi>Now he that is not</hi> infallible <hi>in his counsel, and judgment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fox<hi>'s Myst.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>and advice, is not be in</hi> errour? <hi>And are not the Ministers of Christ, the Ministers of the Spirit?—And are they Ministers of Christ that are</hi> fallible? Again, <hi>How can ye be Ministers of the</hi> Spirit, <hi>and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 82</note>
                  <hi>not of the</hi> Letter, <hi>if ye be not</hi> infallible? <hi>And how can they but</hi> delude <hi>people, who are not</hi> infallible?</p>
               <p>What can be said <hi>more,</hi> unless you will allow that your Ministers are not <hi>men,</hi> or <hi>women,</hi> or not Ministers of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and that they <hi>delude</hi> people? Which two last, though <hi>certainly true,</hi> you will hardly <hi>acknowledge.</hi> Doth <hi>Fox</hi> speak this <hi>to</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Grace of God?</hi> No sure, 'tis <hi>to</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the men and <hi>women</hi> whom you call your <hi>Ministers.</hi> You shew ignorance <hi>enough,</hi> in ascribing Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> it not being an <hi>intelligent Subject.</hi> But such faults may pass, without much notice, in the crowd of your far greater.</p>
               <p>The remaining part of your Piece is <hi>mostly</hi> taken up in <hi>raking</hi> into <hi>old</hi> matters, and removing the <hi>Grave-stone</hi> under which the Kings Favour and Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom had buried them in perpetual <hi>Oblivion:</hi> But as your design therein is no symptom of your meek and <hi>innocent</hi> temper; so I shall not serve your <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> with a wind, by taking farther notice of your <hi>Provocations</hi> therein.</p>
               <p>The Worthy Divines are far from <hi>Culpable,</hi> in advising against <hi>undue</hi> Separation. That it is an evil in <hi>it self,</hi> and mischievous in its <hi>consequence,</hi> is a matter of no <hi>great</hi> doubt; who they <hi>are,</hi> or who they <hi>have been,</hi> that lye under the guilt of it, is <hi>sub Judice:</hi> But of all others, we shall not expect its Determination from a Quaker; whose estimate of all beside <hi>THE FRIENDS,</hi> is, that they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60366:42"/> are no Christians, and so in the greatest incapacity for Christian-Communion: The consideration of which might render it no very hard and <hi>strange</hi> measure, that we should esteem you unworthy of that <hi>name,</hi> having <hi>such</hi> grounds for <hi>so</hi> doing.</p>
               <p>You often cry out against our <hi>uncharitable</hi> Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, as if there were no such things in the World as the <hi>evils</hi> you are <hi>charged</hi> with. The Grace, or the <hi>Vertue either</hi> of Charity is no such <hi>blind</hi> thing, as to shut its eyes against the <hi>clearest</hi> evidences of <hi>Guilt;</hi> or to call <hi>Poyson</hi> by <hi>lovely</hi> names, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons might not <hi>abhor</hi> to be tampering with it; or discern the difference between the things that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company <hi>Salvation,</hi> and those which shut the Gate of Heaven, and the favour of God against the souls of men.</p>
               <p>It would be a token of <hi>Insolency,</hi> as well as <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> for Malefactors <hi>convicted</hi> by the <hi>clearest</hi> Evidence, to cry out, <hi>O your Charity! Is this your Charity!</hi> when they are <hi>justly</hi> censured. If this were a good Plea against all <hi>Accusations;</hi> it were a merry World with the greatest <hi>Offenders,</hi> who would have an <hi>easie</hi> remedy against <hi>those</hi> sufferings, which <hi>alone</hi> (with them) can secure others from their <hi>injuries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>special</hi> Grace you <hi>scoff,</hi> in a pretended favour of <hi>Morality.</hi> If you were qualified with <hi>either,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>'s Reb.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.</note> you were by far a <hi>better</hi> man than you <hi>are.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take Pride, Lying, Dissembling, Revenge, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding, Slandering, Immodesty, to be the <hi>Symptoms</hi> of the one or the <hi>other.</hi> You have little to <hi>shew</hi> for your <hi>Morality,</hi> except your preferring it before <hi>spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace,</hi> by an <hi>undue</hi> Commendation. If to be possessed of such a <hi>good</hi> thing, were but to <hi>talk</hi> on its behalf, many would be <hi>enriched</hi> with it, who have scarce a <hi>rag</hi> of it to <hi>shew.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60366:42"/>
               <p> I suppose your <hi>design</hi> herein was, to carry fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with <hi>some</hi> who have of <hi>late</hi> vented things of <hi>that</hi> nature, as bespeak themselves to be none of the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of the Church they <hi>pretend</hi> to. But while you <hi>seem</hi> to hug Morality, your Kindness for it is as <hi>deceitful,</hi> as for the Christian Principles you in <hi>words</hi> embrace.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Morality</hi> is a <hi>word,</hi> whose sence is hardly <hi>defined,</hi> yet 'tis generally understood to be, what is within the reach of the light and powers of <hi>Nature,</hi> without the Auxiliaries of Divine Revelation, and <hi>special</hi> assistance of the <hi>Spirit of Grace.</hi> But that Light which <hi>you</hi> say is in <hi>every</hi> man and by which, and whose powers only, they ought (as you say) to be informed and moved, you <hi>abhor</hi> to call a <hi>Natural</hi> Light, or that which is less than a Divine and <hi>increated</hi> thing. You hold it to be at such a distance from <hi>Humane</hi> Reason, that where-ever <hi>it</hi> rules, <hi>Reasonings</hi> have no place. So that <hi>here</hi> you and your <hi>Moralists,</hi> and your Morality too, must part to as great a distance, as <hi>Humane Reason</hi> is from the <hi>highest Enthusiasm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is, your fawnings on Persons or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (except your <hi>own)</hi> are as <hi>treacherous,</hi> as your Invectives are <hi>virulent.</hi> You flatter a Worthy Person, whose Learning and Discretion you mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Page</hi> 28.</note> because he was not of the number of the <hi>One and twenty Divines:</hi> Yet while you <hi>kiss</hi> him, you <hi>betray</hi> him, by fastening a Sentence on him as its <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> not very <hi>grateful</hi> to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Perhaps you <hi>intended</hi> to smite him under the <hi>fifth rib,</hi> for applying to the Quakers so <hi>roundly</hi> (in his late Sermons) the Contents of that <hi>dreadful</hi> Text, Heb. 6. 6. <hi>If they shall fall away, to renew them again to Repentance, seeing they crucifie to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60366:43"/> the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The close of your Pamphlet, is a magnifying <hi>the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb.</hi> p. 31.</note>
                  <hi>Ʋniversal Principle in the Conscience,</hi> or Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ascribing to it those things, which are only applicable to the Spirit, or Christ of God. This is your <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the sum and substance of <hi>your</hi> Gospel; according to the saying of your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>W. Smith, And this is the end of our Doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atechis.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 95.</note>
                  <hi>to bring people to the everlasting Word of God in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves;</hi> or a Christ within, which is all <hi>one</hi> with you.</p>
               <p>I must not let your <hi>Postscript</hi> pass without a <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,</hi> which is very fit to be the <hi>tail</hi> of your Book, it being as plain and evident a <hi>tale,</hi> as you could likely utter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for his Appendix</hi> (say you) <hi>it is an arrant cheat, obtruded on the Reader.</hi> These are <hi>hard</hi> words, and a very unfriendly <hi>parting.</hi> But 'tis a comfort when <hi>your self</hi> bring the <hi>Antidote</hi> so near the <hi>Poyson,</hi> in the <hi>Reason</hi> you give for your <hi>Rashness: The Title-page</hi> (you say) <hi>bespeaks it a new Piece, when it is no other in the matter, and for a great part of the words of it, than what hath been answered by me again and again;</hi> 1. <hi>Two Letters of our Friends,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Title-page</hi> bespeaks it <hi>new,</hi> any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>every</hi> Title-page bespeaks the matter of the Book it relates to <hi>new,</hi> is untrue; and that the matter of it is <hi>no other</hi> but what you have answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is as false.</p>
               <p>You do not <hi>honour your Creed,</hi> by shewing so much <hi>displeasure</hi> at its <hi>Repetition</hi> (if it were <hi>such.)</hi> But for the <hi>words</hi> being a great part the <hi>same</hi> you have <hi>answered;</hi> you might as well say the <hi>Letters</hi> are the same of which the <hi>Words</hi> are composed, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60366:43"/> you had confuted the Alphabet. Away with this vanity!</p>
               <p>You say, you have <hi>justified</hi> the two Letters: The more is your <hi>shame.</hi> Tell me, if you can; what <hi>one passage</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the Books which I have <hi>cited</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies out of, which you have <hi>not justified?</hi> or at least, which you have condemned as guilty of <hi>Infirmity,</hi> though they are stuffed with <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> as well as <hi>Errour.</hi> I shall here repeat one of your <hi>justified Letters</hi> to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> because this may fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of <hi>some,</hi> who may not meet with it <hi>elsewhere.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DEar</hi> George Fox, <hi>Who art the</hi> Father <hi>of many</hi> Nations, <hi>whose</hi> Life <hi>hath reached through us thy Children, even to the Isles</hi> afar off; <hi>to the begetting of many again to a lively Hope, for which</hi> Generations to come shall call thee Blessed; <hi>whose</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Habitation <hi>is in the Power of the Highest, in which thou Rules and Governs in</hi> Righteousness: <hi>And</hi> thy <hi>Kingdom is esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in Peace, and the encrease thereof is</hi> without end.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Josiah Coal.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Now let others, who are <hi>yet</hi> in their <hi>wits</hi> judg, how <hi>just</hi> those things are which you dare under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to <hi>justifie;</hi> and what there is of <hi>injustice</hi> in <hi>the</hi> things you <hi>condemn?</hi> The righteous God hath said, <hi>He that justifieth the wicked, and he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60366:44"/> the just; even they both are abomination to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have done with your <hi>Ʋnjust REBƲKE,</hi> &amp;c. and shall now take a <hi>little</hi> notice of <hi>your</hi> carriage in <hi>your</hi> Writings, and what manner of <hi>Censure they</hi> deserve. You have made a huge noise of 400 things you have <hi>faulted</hi> me with in the Conduct (as you call it) of my Books against you. You might as <hi>easily</hi> have said 4000; for I doubt not but you counted every <hi>word</hi> and <hi>letter</hi> therein, under an <hi>ill Conduct,</hi> while managed against Quakerism; but what your word is <hi>worth,</hi> I have already made manifest. And now being a <hi>clear</hi> man, I am the more <hi>competent</hi> Witness against <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, I charge you with three <hi>bulky, wilful Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths,</hi> which I will not call <hi>Lies</hi> for <hi>civility</hi> sake. The first was a <hi>plot</hi> to spoil the <hi>credit</hi> of my Books, within <hi>three</hi> months of their first Impression: <hi>Or else</hi> (say you) <hi>what means his great pains to be made wast paper of already? QƲAKERISM NO CHRISTIANITY, has exchang'd the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nsw. to</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld. <hi>p.</hi> 67.</note>
                  <hi>stalls, for the Tobacco shops: Poor man! Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he will write another Book to complain of the deadness of Professors hearts, that they make so ill use of the Labours of painful Ministers. I am confident, nothing but his fear of losing by it, could divert him from such a Lamentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This passage carries its <hi>name</hi> in its <hi>fore-head.</hi> But the Book-sellers have given it a sufficient <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation,</hi> and a <hi>broad</hi> brand for an <hi>impudent Falshood,</hi> in their Certificate signed by <hi>Jonat. Robinson,</hi> and <hi>Rob. Boulter,</hi> and printed with my <hi>Vindication of Quakerism no Christianity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The second is a <hi>bloody</hi> one, and looks like a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> P<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nsw. to</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. <hi>p.</hi> 199.</note>
                  <hi>blood-thirsty</hi> one: <hi>Not Garments rolled in the blood of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60366:44"/> Kings, Princes, Rulers, and People, no worldly Armies, Battels, Victories, Trophies, Spoils, Sequestrations, Decimations, and the like Blood-thirsty, and Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Projects; in which</hi> John Faldo, <hi>and his poor Non-conforming Ministers, have had their hands over head and ears, till they had well-nigh lost their ears, and their heads too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is the <hi>Comment</hi> on the Quakers boasted <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,</hi> Meekness, Patience, and <hi>Truth.</hi> And that you are not only <hi>mischievous</hi> herein, but <hi>false,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now but entring on my <hi>forty second</hi> year, will render the truth of what you say concerning me <hi>impossible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third <hi>wilful</hi> untruth I charge you with is, your saying, <hi>Let it be observed;</hi> 1. <hi>That I gave him</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Retu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to</hi> Faldo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Curb,</hi> p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> timely notice <hi>of our</hi> Wheeler-street <hi>Meeting, with an</hi> Invitation <hi>to be there; and went more in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, than</hi> T. Hicks, <hi>from a report that</hi> T. H. <hi>would not, but that</hi> John Faldo <hi>intended to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That you gave me any notice of it <hi>at all,</hi> I need no other testimony but my own Conscience, that it is a <hi>falshood;</hi> much less did you give me <hi>timely</hi> notice, and an <hi>invitation</hi> to be there.</p>
               <p>Having the occasion of <hi>once more</hi> encountring you in <hi>Print,</hi> and intending not to let pass this <hi>untruth of yours,</hi> I fairly sent a Letter to you; wherein I desired you (that I might do you <hi>no</hi> injustice) to let me know by what means you sent me the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>timely notice and invitation, and by whom</hi> it was <hi>reported,</hi> that I <hi>intended</hi> to be there. To which you replied first, by an untruth; viz. <hi>That I did not deny either that I was informed, or invited.</hi> But I <note place="margin">Adv. be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no Christ</note> had denied it, if my saying in Print, <hi>I take it to be a plotted untruth,</hi> be a <hi>denying</hi> it.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60366:45"/>
               <p> But although you took <hi>two days</hi> time to return me an Answer, the most certain intelligence you could afford me, and the <hi>best</hi> you had to say for your <hi>self</hi> was, <hi>My Message to thee by</hi> J. Robinson, <hi>if I mistake not, expressed the substance of the matter, that I invited thee to the next Meeting with the Baptists, and fairly promised thee time to say</hi> out thy <hi>say.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binson</hi>'s Certificate determine this.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="statement">
                           <p>
                              <hi>OF the</hi> Wheeler-street <hi>Meeting, and Mr.</hi> Penn<hi>'s Invitation of Mr.</hi> Faldo <hi>to be</hi> there, <hi>I never had the least order or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice from Mr.</hi> Penn, <hi>or any other.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Jonat. Robinson.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p n="4">4. Untruth. <hi>But what is become of that greedy appetite</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Retur.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faldo<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rb,</hi> p. 9.</note>
                  <hi>in Learned and Ʋnlearned after his Books, not only cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by the Book-sellers, but with a most nauseous self-glorying proclaimed by himself in his VINDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICATION.</hi> Not one word of this is true, nor is there any such thing in the Book-sellers Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate, nor any thing like it in my <hi>VINDICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION:</hi> 'Tis too true of you, <hi>Aut inveniam aut faciam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>But he hath told us very seasonably, his farther writing is not deemed convenient or satisfactory.</hi> A <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi> p. 10.</note> gross Forgery!</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>But this Age hath no kindness for Good-works, the more the pity; loose men sleight them in Life, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb. to</hi> 21 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ivines,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 30.</note> you <hi>in Doctrine. A man cannot plead for them, but at</hi> the hazard <hi>of being counted a Papist.</hi> Untruth and <hi>Treachery</hi> wrapt together! A <hi>Whip</hi> for all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and a <hi>Curry-favour</hi> with those you are too
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60366:45"/> near of Kin to, the <hi>meritorious</hi> Romanists: Whom we never desire should practise their <hi>Good-works</hi> on <hi>us.</hi> And I fear you will prove <hi>Co-workers</hi> with them in works bad enough.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He affirms, <hi>That he quoted fourty places out of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Rej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to</hi> Faldo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 425.</note>
                  <hi>our Friends Books, that would prove the Light</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as within us) <hi>to be the only Lord and Saviour, and very God.</hi> This is a down-right <hi>Forgery,</hi> and as <hi>easily</hi> proved to be <hi>such,</hi> as looking into the place in my Book you pretend to transcribe. Who <note place="margin">Fal. <hi>Vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> p. 6.</note> finds the words <hi>Within, as within us</hi> there, must have a faculty with <hi>P.</hi> to read the words were never written.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Preaching, Praying, and that Scripturally too</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> p. 130. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Quak.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Christ.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 155. imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> last.</note> (by him called <hi>Christian-Ordinances) are by him made natural to all Nations.</hi> An Untruth, built upon both a corrupting <hi>my</hi> words, and foisting in some of your <hi>own:</hi> A practice to be <hi>abhorred,</hi> and by which you may say what <hi>you list,</hi> and make me <hi>prove it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. He confidently affirms, <hi>God to be more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P's <hi>Answ</hi> p. 130. <hi>Quak. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Christ.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 156. last impres.</note>
                  <hi>to vindicate the former; and take vengeance for the breach of his positive exterior Precepts; as the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial part of the Jews Worship, and the Bread, Wine, and Water</hi> Sacramentally us'd now-a-days (if yet, as such, they may be accounted Precepts) which the Devil himself can creep into the Profession of, and cannot cleanse as concerning the Conscience; <hi>then of his Fundamental, Natural, and Substantial Laws and Ordinances, without which God cannot be worshipped, nor one Soul saved.</hi> All this you say, I <hi>affirm,</hi> and give it as my <hi>own</hi> words, as well as my <hi>sense,</hi> in a different Letter, except what is in the <hi>Common</hi> Letter in <hi>this</hi> passage. M. <hi>P.</hi> you write at random, no ground will hold <hi>you,</hi> nor the Bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Truth be any <hi>Law</hi> to you.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60366:46"/> 10. Another of the <hi>like</hi> nature, or a <hi>worse,</hi> you have in the <hi>same</hi> page: <hi>From whence</hi> (say you) John Faldo <hi>infers against us, that the Body Christ took upon himself of our nature, is not the Christ.</hi> My inference was in these very words; <q>This is a plain denying the <hi>man</hi> Christ Jesus, whose body of flesh was of <hi>our</hi> nature.</q> But the truth is, you were so put to it in <hi>answering</hi> my Chapter of your <hi>denying the Christ of God,</hi> that you wrote like a man <hi>beside your self:</hi> And as you past by <hi>ten Citations</hi> I produced to prove my Charge, and <hi>attempted</hi> to take off <hi>two only;</hi> so to those <hi>two</hi> you talked so <hi>idly,</hi> as signified you knew not <hi>what</hi> to say, nor well what you <hi>did</hi> say. And any body will conclude with <hi>me,</hi> who shall find your Chapter in answer to this Charge, almost <hi>wholly</hi> taken up in proving, that the <hi>mere</hi> body of Christ, is not the <hi>intire</hi> Christ; which was to confute <hi>John a Nokes,</hi> and not <hi>John Faldo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is a small thing for you to <hi>slander</hi> and <hi>forge,</hi> to the abuse of such an insignificant thing as I; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing those <hi>great</hi> men, Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> and Dr. <hi>More</hi> cannot <hi>escape</hi> you.</p>
               <p>You tell me, that Dr. <hi>More</hi> saith, <q>But the Atheist will still hang on, and object further, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r.</hi> Hen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ore, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yst. God.</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 222.</note> that the very term <hi>Resurrectio</hi> implies, That the same body shall rise again: for that only that <hi>falls</hi> can be said <hi>properly</hi> to rise again.</q> Here you make your Application to me in these words; <hi>Where let the Reader take notice, that Dr.</hi> More <hi>calls</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>'s Rejoy.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faldo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 374.</note> John Faldo <hi>ATHEIST; for it is his Objection against me,</hi> Reply, <hi>p.</hi> 89.</p>
               <p>Here are two things you are to be <hi>indicted</hi> for; first, making my Opinion to be the <hi>Atheists</hi> about the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> which the Atheist mostly <hi>objects</hi> against, and is stumbled at. Doth Dr. <hi>More</hi> say,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60366:46"/> that the Atheist <hi>holds</hi> such a Resurrection, who denies <hi>any</hi> Resurrection at all? <hi>Ʋnhappy Writers</hi> would the most Learned be, if there were no more able, careful, and faithful Readers and <hi>Reporters</hi> of what they <hi>read</hi> than <hi>W. Penn!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the second which I intended by this of Dr. <hi>More</hi> (which you abuse) is, that you say Dr. <hi>More</hi> calls <hi>me Atheist</hi> in this Section; whereas the Dr. saith <hi>expresly,</hi> by way of <hi>Caution,</hi> before this Section; <q>This I say to the Atheist, not to those who hold the substance [of the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Learned and much-respected Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penn<hi>'s Rejoyn.</hi> Faldo, <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 378.</note> you make a partaker of your Heresie; in telling me, that Dr. <hi>Hammond also denies a proper and strict Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of bodies, and consequently is guilty of that horrid Principle as</hi> John Faldo <hi>calls it: Which may be seen in his Comment,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. O horrible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation! Neither the Doctor nor I call it a <hi>Strict,</hi> &amp;c. And he saith there as much as can be said for my Opinion, but not one word against it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> I have here given twelve of your <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries,</hi> or Falshoods in <hi>fact:</hi> If you will adventure to clear your self of <hi>these,</hi> without your <hi>usual</hi> defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one untruth (in point of fact) by adding more of the like ill qualities; I will promise to furnish you with an account of <hi>fourty</hi> more of the <hi>like</hi> nature. I never read any man who replied to your <hi>Defences,</hi> who have not accused you of <hi>wilful</hi> untruths in point of <hi>fact,</hi> which is an ill symptom of your <hi>guilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not <hi>greatly</hi> wonder, that you write so <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly</hi> against those who <hi>oppose</hi> you, when 'tis so <hi>apparent,</hi> that besides the defect of Truth and <hi>Conscience,</hi> your Writings have not the Conduct of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60366:47"/>
                  <hi>common Prudence;</hi> but you are as <hi>inconsistent</hi> with your <hi>self,</hi> as you are with <hi>Truth,</hi> and need no other Condemnation but what proceeds out of your <hi>own</hi> mouth. For the proof of <hi>which,</hi> compare your <hi>self</hi> with your <hi>self,</hi> in the following passages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will rather</hi> (say you) <hi>betake my self to single</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n's <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sw. to</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldo, <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note>
                  <hi>out the strength of his Objections, if any there be, and bestow my time in Vindication of the Truth, than to rail, revile, undervalue, and stigmatize with I know not how many disgraceful Epithetes; a way that never yet reached any man's Conscience—A Bannian is a Saint to a Congregation of such Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Bravely said! and that's all.</p>
               <p>Would not any man expect (who knows you not) to meet with most <hi>calm</hi> and <hi>candid</hi> lines from so fair a <hi>Talker?</hi> yet the very <hi>next</hi> words of yours, calls my Book a Discourse <hi>interterlined with Babling and Prattle.</hi> I hope no man will think you overva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue your Adversaries Writings, who in your <hi>best mood,</hi> can give them <hi>such</hi> a Character, and be at the charge of giving your self the—in the <hi>same</hi> breath.</p>
               <p>Let us hear you once more <hi>proclaim</hi> your <hi>sweet</hi> temper. <hi>I omit</hi> (say you) <hi>more than an hundred</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>'s Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Truth,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.</note>
                  <hi>things, that would engage to a personal reflection; for my Soul hath no pleasure in striving therein, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the</hi> inconsistency <hi>of that uncharitable virulent temper with a</hi> Christian <hi>spirit; which I am sure is quite another thing for what is Verbose, Abusive, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing, Airy, and merely Notional.</hi> Truly I have <hi>more Charity</hi> for you, than you have for your <hi>self:</hi> For although I take not <hi>very uncivil</hi> Language, and <hi>undue</hi> personal Reflections to be your <hi>goodness;</hi> yet had I no <hi>other</hi> Arguments against you but your <hi>bad</hi> Carriage in <hi>this</hi> kind, I might hope you were a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60366:47"/> Christian <hi>notwithstanding.</hi> But let us see at how cheap a rate you will <hi>forfeit your Christianity,</hi> and the good <hi>effects</hi> of your Writings on the Readers <hi>Conscience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall rake into but <hi>one</hi> of your Books for all the following good Language, and leave large gleanings. All these <hi>lovely</hi> Titles and Epithetes you afford <hi>me,</hi> and my work, <hi>Behold your Priest!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W. Penn. <hi>Answ. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Fal. <hi>Pre.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. 43. 65. 79. 64. 209<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 117. 190. 208. 216. 74. 107. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 49. 46. 110<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 157. 204. 213. 214. 203. 215.</note>
                  <hi>Fallible, errable Priest. Scoffing, Independent Priest. Ʋngodly Priest. Busie Priest. Cavilling Priest. Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing Priests. Antichristian Priest. Mountebank Priest. This Taunting Priest. Stingie Priests. Mercenary</hi> John Faldo. <hi>A Quack. A Religious Bone-setter. The Priests Break-neck. The Priest and his Puppe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-play Doctrine. Vaunting, strutting</hi> John Faldo. <hi>Insolent Vilifier. Ignorance, or Malice it self. Our malignant Adversary</hi> J. Faldo. <hi>Ignorance, Malice, and Revenge, Black as Hell it self in malice. Impious Scoffs. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence. Strange Impudence. The impudence of his Wickedness. Sordid Pedantry. He Vomits. His Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he brings, no more to purpose, than</hi> Tobie <hi>and his Dog. Oh Doctrine of Devils! A Lye. A Lye to be sure. A very Lye. Devilish Falsities. A down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Lye. An arrant Lye. A wicked Lye. The last great Lye of his second part of Lyes. A wicked Lye minted out of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not here <hi>enough</hi> to advance you to be Master of the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or Gentleman of the <hi>Black rod,</hi> to the Confusion of all <hi>Railers?</hi> yet these are but your <hi>Retale-vent;</hi> for such mild, <hi>melting</hi> Language, you have also a <hi>Wholesale-</hi>Trade, by which you dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge whole Loads, or Vollies <hi>together,</hi> enough to make a man out of breath with repeating them.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60366:48"/>
               <p> Behold two examples: <hi>Such Covenant-breaking,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi> Faldo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>20.</note>
                  <hi>Self-seeking, Club-law</hi> (hitherto you are very preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and bring forth your kind Epithets by cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) <hi>Proud, Covetous, Tyrannical, Persecuting Priests we could never own; but EVER did, and ever shall bear our faithful testimony against them, as the Locusts, Caterpillars, Serpents, and Dragons of the Earth; whose Cruelty, Self-seeking, and Falseness hath grieved good-men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <hi>But in the Earth there is not any thing so fantastical, conceited,, proud, railing, busie-body, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 165.</note>
                  <hi>sometimes ignorant, as a sort of Priests, to me not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known (among whom our Adversary is not the least) who think their Coat will bear out their worst expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Religion, and practice an haughty reviling for Christ, as one of the greatest Demonstrations of their zeal. An ill-bred and pedantick Creco, the bane of Reason, and pest of the World, the old Incondiaries to mischief, and the best to be spared of mankind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is this the man whose Soul hath no <hi>pleasure</hi> in Revilings, and <hi>personal</hi> Reflections? Dost thou teach others, and <hi>teachest not thy self?</hi> Is there a plainer evidence of a down-right Hypocrite? But methinks the <hi>innocency,</hi> candor, peaceableness, and good-will which you <hi>pretend</hi> to <hi>all men,</hi> has but a poor evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in <hi>these</hi> lines. And your saying, that I espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially am one of those who are the <hi>pest of the World, and the best to be spared of Mankind,</hi> is no other in the true English of it, than that I ought to be preferred to the <hi>Gallows,</hi> or any other <hi>execution,</hi> rather than a Thief or Murtherer. The Lord be merciful to us, and deliver us out of your hands, whose tongues and pens being at <hi>liberty,</hi> are so sharp a sword, and sentence us to death, while your <hi>hands</hi> cannot exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the <hi>thoughts</hi> of your <hi>hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60366:48"/>
               <p> You commend your selves for <hi>an innocent people,</hi> and you close your Answer to me with <hi>this.</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Who am a lover of all men, for I seek the Salvation of mine Enemies,</hi> William Penn. But did you mean as you say, it will not hold always. But if you be once in the angry spirit, their <hi>Salvation</hi> must be interpreted their ruine and <hi>destruction.</hi> What else mean these lines, and what I shall further add out of the <hi>same</hi> Book, wherein you break through the Law of God and man, to be revenged on me, and many more who (for ought you know) never lift up a tongue against your culpable Tenets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why poor Nonconformists</hi> (say you) after all <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 109<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> their preach'd up Battels, Spoils, <hi>Plunders, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Decimations?</hi> Again, <hi>Not Garments roll'd in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 119<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>the blood of Kings, Princes, Rulers, and People: no worldly Armies, Battels, Victories, Trophies, Spoils, Decimations, and the like blood-thirsty and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical projects, in which</hi> John Faldo <hi>and his poor Non-conforming Ministers have had their hands over head and ears, till they had well-nigh lost their ears, and their heads too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the sense of this? its base and cruel coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance speaks the spirit from whence it came, to be a mischievous one. The Lord forgive you, and give you the knowledg of your self, and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Votaries, a deliverance from your <hi>Conduct,</hi> and others from your <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This puts me in mind of your glorying, that you had killed an old Priest (as you call him) with your Answer to his Book written against your Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: And you tell me the story thus; <hi>There was an old peevish Priest in</hi> Ireland, T. Jenner, <hi>who writ an envious Book against us—who lived long enough to vex himself to</hi> death <hi>with our</hi> Answer <hi>(as
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60366:49"/> we are credibly informed) not long surviving its ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival.</hi> Rejoynd. <hi>to</hi> Faldo, p. 172.</p>
               <p>Is not this a piece of Vanity, which rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us what you <hi>would</hi> do, and how pleasant the conceit of <hi>killing</hi> your Adversaries is to you, than of the <hi>effects</hi> of your Writings? for the good-man was about seventy years old, and therefore very likely that he died no such <hi>untimely</hi> death.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You are no such Basilisk to kill at that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and I am like enough to be safe from your <hi>close</hi> encounters. Your Writings may be like what the Poets <hi>feign</hi> of <hi>Pandora</hi>'s <hi>Box,</hi> which when opened, filled the World with many <hi>plagues:</hi> But the Grace of God, and a few grains of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, is defensative enough against the <hi>danger.</hi> If you thought I would <hi>die too</hi> upon the conceit of your story of Mr. <hi>Jenner,</hi> you are much mistaken: I am not such a <hi>Milk-sop,</hi> but I hope I shall be a better Souldier of <hi>Jesus Christ of</hi> Nazareth, than to fall or <hi>faint</hi> under all your Rage, Reviling, and Reproaches.</p>
               <p>I intended to have gratified my Reader, with the <hi>Counter-Scuffle</hi> you make with your <hi>own self,</hi> in all or <hi>most</hi> of the <hi>main</hi> points I charge you as erring in: But to keep within the bounds of a few sheets, I shall only present your <hi>contrary Aspects</hi> on the holy Scriptures, and that briefly, in your following Sayings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But also as we acknowledg them to be the Words of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penn<hi>'s Answ. to</hi> Faldo, <hi>p.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>53.</note>
                  <hi>the holy, living, and powerful word of God, so that they express and declare unto us many holy Rules for godliness—And I declare, in the name of all the right Quakers in the World, that we utterly reject all such as deny the Scriptures to be profitable for Reprehension, Instruction, Exhortation, and Edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60366:49"/>
               <p> By this a <hi>common</hi> Reader would think you have a huge <hi>respect</hi> for the Scripture: But let us see the <hi>other</hi> side of your <hi>Countenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This choaks</hi> John Faldo (say you) <hi>and the rest of his Partners—who dread the Consequence of having their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>litteral knowledg of the Scriptures laid aside.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No Command in the Scripture is any farther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon any man, than as he finds a conviction upon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>his Conscience: Otherwise men should be engaged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, if not against conviction, a thing unreasonable in man; therefore the Apostle when he wrote to the Churches, exhorted them not to do those things whereof they were ashamed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then if they were not by a convicted Conscience ashamed, they could not sin: Right Ranter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dry cavilling Lettermongers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Truth,</hi> &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to think to run us down, by exalting them; or to lessen what we are, by encreasing their praise, is an old Artifice of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But let it suffice, that</hi> John Faldo <hi>steals as bad as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penn<hi>'s Answ. to</hi> Fald. <hi>p.</hi> 38<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Jeremiah<hi>'s neighbours did, and thus far more boldly and notoriously, in that they perhaps got the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets words so soon, that some might not know who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P<hi>'s Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oy. to</hi> Faldo, <hi>p.</hi> 156.</note>
                  <hi>had them first; whereas</hi> J. F. <hi>runs back two or three thousand years</hi> a pilferring <hi>for his</hi> hackney <hi>Sermons out of</hi> them, <hi>which are so well known to be other mens lines and labours. Methinks people should not suffer themselves to be so miserably</hi> gull'd, <hi>nor lie at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of maintaining a Priest to tell his tales,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Not boasting of things beyond our measure, that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id.</hi> p. 151.</note> is of other mens labours, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 15. <hi>Of this sort of boasters is</hi> John Faldo, <hi>who hath nothing for his Religion but the mere Bible, and but an usurpt title to that.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60366:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith in</hi> John Faldo<hi>'s sense, rises no higher than so many Articles laid down (suppose truly) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the bare letter of the Scripture, which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. 71.</note>
                  <hi>ean believe as well as he.</hi> A slander to boot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They could not run their Canon higher than the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et. Soan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fau.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note>
                  <hi>Council of</hi> Laodicea; <hi>which, as we said before, was</hi> 364 <hi>years after Christ: At what time,</hi> says a great Author, Ambition prevailed with the Doctors of the Church, and they began to think of holy <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Penn<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ejoynder</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faldo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 37.</note> Cheats, and would have their Doctrines pass for Laws, not Counsel. This wretched saying you <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose not,</hi> but embrace as your very dear Friend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot but observe after what a suspected rate the Scriptures have been first collected, and then convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi> p. 38.</note>
                  <hi>through the several succeeding Ages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From hence we may observe the uncertainty of</hi> John <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi> p. 39.</note> Faldo's <hi>Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet the running Title of your <hi>ANSWER</hi> is, <hi>The Quakers own the Scriptures.</hi> I will not concal, that you say after your unworthy detractions, <hi>Far be it from me to write this in any undervalue of that holy Record.</hi> But 'tis as small amends, as to say to a man, after you have stab'd him to the heart, far be it from me to hurt you. And indeed the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture must be valued at a very low rate, for you to say of them they are <hi>undervalued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There remains now only <hi>one Question</hi> to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; and that is, Whether Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> or I have dealt <hi>faithfully</hi> in matter of <hi>fact,</hi> and made true Reports of what depends only on <hi>so much</hi> Reason, as to know whether we read such and such <hi>words;</hi> and so much <hi>honesty,</hi> as not to report <hi>contrary</hi> to our knowledge? If what Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> hath charged on me in the <hi>most</hi> of his Ten Instances be <hi>true,</hi> I may pass for an Idiot, or worse; but if <hi>false,</hi> I am loth to call him by his proper name.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60366:50"/>
               <p> Those who have my <hi>QƲAKERISM NO CHRISTIANITY,</hi> and my <hi>VINDICA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION</hi> by them, may as easily determine of <hi>most</hi> of them, as to read English. With those who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with his Charges, he will be known to be what he is; and that is worse than most mens <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> will give them leave to <hi>censure,</hi> till undeniable evidence hath left no room for <hi>better</hi> thoughts.</p>
               <p>It is in vain to trouble the World with an answer to every thing a man writes, who doth not so much as <hi>intend</hi> honesty, nor makes any Conscience of <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> abusing his Adversary by perfect Forgeries. He that is thus guilty, frequently and designedly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves to be <hi>hissed</hi> out of Christian, yea <hi>Humane Society,</hi> as one against whose Injuries there is no defence, but a detection of his <hi>hateful</hi> qualities.</p>
               <p>I have for determining matters of fact, provoked him in print, to give me a meeting in these terms.</p>
               <p>In the close of my <hi>VINDICATION</hi> I say, <q>To conclude, I shall desire Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> (if he dare <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vindic: Quak. no Christian.</hi> p. 95.</note> come to that test) to appoint some of his Friends, (that can but read English) to give me a meeting, and I <hi>do</hi> promise to make it appear to them, that he hath in abundance of places <hi>egregiously</hi> played the <hi>Forger,</hi> foisting into my Sentences words of his <hi>own,</hi> to serve his <hi>design;</hi> yea, and framing <hi>whole Sentences,</hi> and calling them <hi>mine,</hi> which were never in my Book, nor the <hi>sense</hi> of them.</q> This offer was 18 months since, but never accepted.</p>
               <p>Before <hi>this Answer</hi> passed the Press, I engaged di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers persons, of no mean Consideration, to spend a little time in <hi>examining</hi> his <hi>ten</hi> things he charged upon me, to beget an opinion in the Reader of my ignorance and dishonesty. And being thereto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised, I gave him a <hi>friendly Invitation by Letter,</hi> to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60366:51"/> be present at nhe Examinarion, that he might have opportunity to make the <hi>best</hi> of his Cause, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my misrepresenting him to the World, by any mistake on <hi>my</hi> part, if such there should have been. What passed by such a way betwixt him and me, I here faithfully recite.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Have been obliged to consider your <hi>Rebuke,</hi> &amp;c. to One and twenty Divines; in which you have endeavoured to render both them and me so crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that as we tender our own Reputation (beside the concern of Christianity) it stands us upon to vindicate our selves, so far as we are guiltless. In order to which (your Charges being chiefly about matter of fact, and therefore easily determined by comparing our Writings) there are engaged divers Divines, and others, persons of Integrity, Wisdom, and Reputation, to examine them, at Mr.—house, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on <hi>Tuesday</hi> next, at three in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon. I thought meet to give you this Account, and invite you thither; where you will find nothing contrary to Candor, and <hi>genuine</hi> Christianity.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours, <hi>John Faldo.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Jan.</hi> 21. 1674/5</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>J. Faldo,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>NOt to be so rude as to take no notice of thy Letter, of Invitation, nor yet to be injurious to other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious occasions, I thought good to let thee know, that this day, and hour, pitch'd upon by thee, has been fix'd for the dispatch of an affair, above four years standing:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60366:51"/> And had not that otherwise engaged me than to meet thee, the Interment of a loving Friend (punctually given out to be at the same hour intended by her Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) I should gladly have embraced that oportunity: For I heartely love peace, and dispare not of some of the</hi> 21 <hi>better information; though I confess it looks strainge, to examin a Book after recommended. Be it as it will, all your prosperety is sincerely wish'd; and perticuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a disposition to cander and quiet. By</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy Friend,</hi> W. Penn.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>26 11th Month.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>I have given you his Letter exactly. If there be both bad sense, and no very good Orthography, I cannot help <hi>that:</hi> Nor have I time to catch <hi>Flies.</hi> But you may observe how <hi>critically</hi> his <hi>great affairs</hi> fall out for an <hi>excuse;</hi> and how ceremoniously he is addicted (very strange in a <hi>Quaker)</hi> that his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a <hi>dead Corps</hi> to the grave (if there were no other consideration) is preferred by him, before so great a Concern. No doubt but he had Reasons more <hi>Cogent</hi> stood in his way, but they were not to be proclaimed by him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Intellects were not very <hi>quick</hi> about the unseasonableness of examining a a Book <hi>after</hi> Recommendation, unless <hi>his and mine</hi> were to be <hi>compared</hi> before <hi>his</hi> had a <hi>being.</hi> But however, saith he, <hi>Be it as it will</hi> (a desperate case) he wishes us <hi>now</hi> to be <hi>quiet.</hi> He hath had the <hi>last word,</hi> and laid all the dirt at our doors (but of his own making) there let it lie, and 'tis as he would have it. If he had a mind indeed to the opportunity offered, he should have desired some other time; But no mention being made of that. I sent him the following Epistle.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60366:52"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOurs to me, excusing your meeting at the time I proposed (I being desirous that the matters of fact you charge upon me might be examined fairly) I do now propose to you to appoint your own time on any day betwixt this and <hi>Friday</hi> next, or at any hour of the day betwixt eight in the Morning, and seven at night: Provided you give me notice of your resolution therein by to morrow twelve at Noon—The place of meeting may be the same proposed in my last: You may bring four persons with you, and I shall do the like,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours, <hi>John Faldo.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Feb.</hi> 1st, 1674/5</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>P's</hi> Answer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>J. Faldo,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THough I know not to what purpose such meeting will be; yet since it is so much desired on thy part, I will</hi> endeavour <hi>to bend my affairs to a compliance: But to pitch the day and hour,</hi> I can't well do, <hi>yet shall</hi> endeavour <hi>to limit it to this week,</hi> and if I can, <hi>to let it be on the</hi> 5 <hi>day of its about</hi> 10 <hi>in the morning, at the same place. Perhaps thou mayest interpret this</hi> a shyness <hi>in me to meet thee, being very unhappy at draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Consequences: But they that both know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, are well satisfied that very important affairs obstruct. No more occurring, I remain,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Thy Friend,</hi> Will. Penn.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Lond.</hi>
                           <date>2d 12th Month.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60366:52"/>
               <p> This hesitating, irresolute, and excusive Reply, being the most I could procure, I sent him notice that I should not attend his <hi>uncertainties;</hi> I having other matters to mind as well as he, and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from <hi>London.</hi> And that he might hear fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from methe next week; <hi>i. e.</hi> by this Book coming forth.</p>
               <p>It is worth the notice, that in his first Letter he saith, he would gladly have embraced the offered opportunity, were it not for the <hi>lets</hi> mentioned; but when they were <hi>vanished,</hi> and I importune him again, he tells me, he knows not to what purpose it would be (thus true is the man to himself:) Yet that he might <hi>seem</hi> willing, he saith <hi>somewhat;</hi> but that he might not be obliged, he takes great care to say nothing to purpose. But I must not interpret it a shyness in him to <hi>meet me,</hi> least I should be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of drawing an <hi>unhappy</hi> Consequence; that is (as sometimes understood) hit the nail o'th <hi>head.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any such persons as both <hi>know</hi> him, and <hi>believe</hi> him (in matters of this nature) I will not say; but sure I am he hath taught me, as sure as <hi>Sense it self,</hi> that they that <hi>believe</hi> him, do not <hi>know</hi> him. But if it be so, that important affairs still ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct, and his coming to the test must be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by some <hi>vacant</hi> hours, wherein he can find nothing else to do, or say; I do hereby assure him (the Lord sparing me life and liberty) that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is at <hi>leisure,</hi> and shall give me notice of his inclination to a meeting, with <hi>tolerable</hi> circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, I shall gladly embrace it without a <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;</hi> and shall prove, that in in his ten Instances of <hi>my</hi> failings, he hath committed almost, if not altogether, ten <hi>Falsities</hi> in point of <hi>fact,</hi> to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of his <hi>honesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:60366:53"/>
               <p> You among the People <hi>called</hi> Quakers, who are so honest as to <hi>mean</hi> well (of which number I am perswaded there are <hi>many)</hi> 'tis time to look about you, and not trust your <hi>Faith,</hi> on which depends the honour of God, and his Truth, and your Souls eternal Concerns, upon the words of <hi>deceitful</hi> men. Be so industrious, as to try them; and so impartial, as to believe your <hi>own eyes.</hi> Think me not your <hi>Enemy,</hi> who would be glad to be at the cost of many a suffering to undeceive you. The holy Scriptures tells us of some who <hi>speak lies in Hypocrisie,</hi> and who deceive, and are deceived. It will not ease you of your misery in another World, to find your Perverters having the greater share, as they have been the greater <hi>sinners.</hi> Be not so charitable to <hi>others,</hi> as to be cruel to your selves. Quickly after the Apostles days, there were men of the <hi>same</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion with your Leaders; of whom <hi>Irenaeus</hi> gave that account, the <hi>Latin</hi> of which I put into the <hi>Title-page,</hi> and with its English I conclude the Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>While that Hereticks speak like the faithful, they not only mean otherwise than they say, hut clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And by their Tenets full of Blasphemies, they destroy the Souls of those, who with their fair words, suck in the poyson of their foul opinions.</hi> Irenaeus in his 3 Book against Heresies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 36. <hi>line</hi> 30. <hi>for</hi> specifically, <hi>read</hi> generically, <hi>page</hi> 38. <hi>line</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> hide, <hi>read</hi> countenance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60366:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>